Easwaran Jayaraman: During a review.
Easwaran Jayaraman: Man, baby.
germayne: Yeah, yes, yes, Jaya, I can't hear you.
Easwaran Jayaraman: Excellent. Thank you.
germayne: Okay, good evening, everyone. Good evening, good evening.
germayne: I wonder how are you guys feeling? We are at 3.6.
germayne: So, to some extent, we are, like, 60%… we are 60% done with this.
germayne: Very fast, right? I think it's about… excluding this week, I think it's just 2 more… 2 more weeks.
germayne: So, I think to some extent, I've been with you guys for 20 weeks?
germayne: Maybe it's slightly more than that.
germayne: Sorry, what am I saying? 20… Oh, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, it's 20 weeks.
germayne: Okay, okay, so those of you, if you are… if you are… if you are convenient and you're back home, then you can… you can turn on your camera. I will… I will start in one minute's time.
germayne: Okay, so good evening, everyone. You guys can… you guys can hear me, right? Can… can you hear me?
germayne: Okay, so… Okay, welcome, welcome back to class for today's lesson. So, on… on… on Tuesday, we have…
germayne: Spend some time talking about what
germayne: What did we talk about on Tuesday?
germayne: We'll talk a bit about some of the unsupervised learning methods, as well as feature transformation.
germayne: So, I think from a… from a… curriculum perspective.
germayne: Today, we are… we are going to take a, you know, a bit of a…
germayne: digress. We're gonna digress a bit to go into time series, and we will share, you know, some introduction to time series, purely introduction.
germayne: you will see later that time series itself is a whole new topic, right? It's a field where you can… you can… you can sort of specialize into time series. I think there's a lot of that
germayne: within time series. So, obviously, I think has an introduction course, for time series especially, what we'll do is we'll just talk about some of the important key areas. We'll introduce one algorithm.
germayne: And I think there'll be some takeaway for you guys to explore, as well as some suggested materials
germayne: Okay, so are you guys, are you guys ready for today's lesson?
germayne: Okay.
germayne: Okay, so I think… I think, as I mentioned, towards the… towards the end of the class, I'll give… I'll give you guys a summary. But for today, right, when we are thinking about time series, it is not… I wouldn't say it's… it's classified as a type of
germayne: category within machine learning, right? Time series, essentially, is a… is a domain itself, right? So if you think about later on for 3.9 and 3.10, where we talk a bit about natural language processing, natural language processing, we are trying to reason about our understanding about text data.
germayne: So today, we are thinking more about time series, right? It's a type of data where, you know, we will also share… I will also share about what kind of domain deals specifically with time series, but essentially, within time series, you can apply supervised learning, unsupervised learning as well.
germayne: Right? But for today's purpose, we are just only going to be focused… focusing specifically on the forecasting aspect, which means, if we can think about it, it's actually just predictive, right?
germayne: Okay, so, so today's… today's class actually will be broken down into four main portions.
germayne: Right? I think the first two is just more about some introduction about what time series exactly means, right?
germayne: It's more of introducing the time series data structure, right? What's so special about time series? What are the cases where you need to deal with time series? We'll spend some time talking about visualization, I think that will be more on the notebook exercise.
germayne: For the third portion, for time series analysis, it's more of, like, the metrics, right? If you think about predictive.
germayne: As you have saw last week, we always need some ways to measure them.
germayne: Well, but thankfully, because
germayne: if you think about predictive, it's really just predicting continuous value. So, some of the metrics that we have seen previously would still come over.
germayne: But for the sake of time series, we'll be introducing, I think for today's lesson, I'll be introducing three
germayne: new metrics, which you can also apply for your typical regression analysis. It's not… not specific for time series, which is why I wouldn't say time series is a category of algorithm. It is not. Time series is more of the data…
germayne: structure, the specific type of data pertaining to certain domain. And of course, finally, at the last part, we'll talk about, we'll introduce one, one…
germayne: classical algorithm. Still used… it's still used occasionally, right? It's not that…
germayne: With machine learning, we totally just throw away the statistical method.
germayne: Okay, I'll share, I'll share with you guys why as well.
germayne: Okay, so I think just to… just to warm up everyone, I'm pretty sure everybody has actually seen before what a time series is. You might not know about this specific definition, but I'm pretty sure everybody has seen it, right? So by definition, if you think about time series.
germayne: Time series is really just specifically defined as when you have a data.
germayne: Give me, like, 2 minutes,
germayne: Okay, so time series, right, by definition, is specifically a type of data that is collected over time, right? So, essentially, time series, we can really just think about sequential data. It just means that there is some kind of data that is associated with some kind of time structure, and…
germayne: Sorry, one… give me one more minute.
germayne: And specifically, they are associated with some kind of structural order.
germayne: Which means that later on, you will see that time series has a specifically defined sequence, right? And this sequence needs to sort of be respected when you think about time series. So, of course, there's a lot of things that are time series based, right? So if you think about things like your stock prices.
germayne: Right? Be it, you know, with different kind of frequency, you essentially have a sequential data. When you think about, like, things like stock prices.
germayne: Let me just try to annotate.
germayne: Oh.
germayne: Right? So if you think about things like your stock prices, essentially, they have some kind of frequency, right? Think about weather pattern, right? What is, like, the next 5 minutes, next 10 minutes? And of course, most importantly, things like your sales.
germayne: Right, so what is the monthly sales figure? What is the daily sales figure? So, essentially, there's some kind of sequence.
germayne: and things like your demand as well, right? Some kind of demand patterns, you know, from 12pm, 12.01, 12.05, there's some kind of sequence. So if you think about it structurally, the data is actually some kind of sequence, right? So we have X1, X2,
germayne: all the way to XN.
germayne: Right? So what this, essentially, later on, you will see is that, you know, when… when… so far, at least the kind of data that we have dealt with are essentially things like your cross-sectional data, right? We are looking at independent data that has no
germayne: structure, or no sequential structure within it, right? If you look at your visual data, each row, each instance, again, right, take note, I like to use the word instance, it's because instance just means that each of your rows of data
germayne: If you look at each rows of your data, they are actually independent, right? Your resale price of row number 1 with ID123,
germayne: is independent with row number 2000, ID456, correct?
germayne: So you can see that the data… the data structure itself is different. But when you think about… when you think about sales data, sorry, if you think about time series data, the structure is important, right? There's no meaning for me to say something like, oh, you know, the stock price of, let's say, Google… Google stock or alphabet stock. It's meaningless for me to say if there's no sequence involved.
germayne: Right? I want it… I need it to be associated with some kind of sequence. So later on, you will see that whenever we want to model such data.
germayne: somehow the model needs to have the inherent sequence being modeled, because it's meaningless without the sequence. But for things like your cross-sectional data, your VCO data.
germayne: the data doesn't need to care about the sequence, right? I'm just looking at each independent data instance independently.
germayne: Okay?
germayne: So, of course, this is super important. Even in econometrics, time series is also always
germayne: mention. Anybody wants to know why. Anybody can tell me why. Why is it in economics? When you think about policy, sometimes you need to think about time series. Any examples?
germayne: From a government or from a policy perspective.
germayne: What kind of data is, like, time series?
germayne: Anybody knows?
Zac Ang: Maybe before and after a policy is enacted?
germayne: but what kind… what kind of… what is the… the specific data point, for example, that we can think of?
Hitesh shah: PP?
Hitesh shah: GDP?
germayne: Yeah, so GDP is one, right? So GDP is also a time series data, just across time. So from a macro perspective, then you are very interested in the GDP has an indicator for the economy, right?
germayne: Then, of course, you also have things like the seasonality, right? Because if it's a time series, there's going to be some kind of seasonal pattern, right? And again, the seasonality cycle depends on the frequency of the data that you're talking about.
germayne: Right? If you're talking about things like demand, if you're thinking from a shopping sales perspective, you might… you might expect some kind of seasonality that is during the holiday periods, correct? You might expect certain spike.
germayne: in your data during December period. And this is a cycle that always happens every fixed interval.
germayne: Of course, things like traffic, right, your traffic data.
germayne: the kind of data that I always, have to work with, right? Your traffic patterns is also seasonal, right? Do you guys agree it's seasonal? Right? At 6, 6pm, when, you know, you guys are all rushing home.
germayne: Right? You'll realize that the train is back.
germayne: So if you want to do some kind of analysis on travel pattern, you know, congestion of the road, congestion of the public transportation, all this data is time series, right? I'm able to think about the pattern of this data using some kind of interval, you know, at 6pm, 6.30,
germayne: 6.45, and it is meaningless to think about them independently.
germayne: Right, of course, financial cycle. I think, Hitesh was saying about GDP. So all your financial indicators, essentially, they are all time series. So you can see time series is actually very, very important, depending on which field you are coming from.
germayne: Right? It depends on your field. I used to do a lot of time series data for demand forecasting, for example. Now I'm doing a time series more of on the traffic patterns.
germayne: Right, but the idea is, if you are specifically working in things like sales, right, you have to look at sales numbers, you have to look at, oh, profit numbers, you have to look at increase in demand.
germayne: or if you are working for a company, if you're doing analytics on consumer goods, for example. I used to have a student, her capstone was about… she worked in one of a very big,
germayne: consumer product, they sell shoes, and they also want to understand some kind of forecast in order to, you know, have some kind of stock take or inventory prediction. So all of these are actually time series, right? That's why it's very, very important.
germayne: Okay?
germayne: Okay, so I think we talked about this already.
germayne: Okay, so I think time series data you will see later on, right? Generally, there's a trend component that you'll want to think about, right? Trend in a sense of, like, the general direction of where the time series is moving.
germayne: Right? So if you, you know, if you are, let's say, doing a lot of technical analysis on stocks, generally you want to understand if the trend is, like, going up or down, right?
germayne: And then you can also think about seasonality, which is what I mentioned, as well as the cycle, right? So, I don't think this definition here is, like, super important, right? It's just basically just telling you, like, what are some of the patterns that you can see in a time series data. So I'll leave this to you guys.
germayne: Hey, sorry.
germayne: Then I pressed the wrong button.
germayne: Okay, so I think what we want to do here is we just want to illustrate a bit of the differences in the data, right?
germayne: Okay? So, just like what I mentioned, time series, by definition, has some kind of sequence, right? And this is very important, because
germayne: you cannot break the sequence of the data, because the order is very important, right? So again, again, if you… if I just want to go to my… my… my…
germayne: Okay, I'm just gonna scroll down.
germayne: Right, so again, I think I just mentioned, if your X data is a sequential data, essentially you have some kind of sequence.
germayne: all the way to XN, right?
germayne: So by definition here, the difference with some of the data that you have been used to is that there's a sequence
germayne: involved, right? Which means that I cannot think of X1 and Xn independently, right? They are all within a sequence. So what this means is that if I want to model them.
germayne: I cannot model them with an assumption that they are independent, right? I cannot… I cannot pretend that X1 and XN is independent, so I need to somehow ensure that the structure is always intact. Now, if you again think in contrast with something like your HDB resio data.
germayne: Right? Your X1 and X2 are just basically two separate independent samples of resale flats, right?
germayne: X1 might be a specific flat, right, with ID, I don't know, 1, 2, 3.
germayne: Right? It doesn't really matter, if I shuffle ID 123 with XN and X1, even if I swap the position of XN and X1, it doesn't matter. But for time series data, you cannot do that, right? You have to ensure that the structure… again, right?
germayne: my take… what I'm trying to say is that it's not that you cannot shuffle them. If you want to shuffle them, you need to think of some way to encode the position. Essentially, the position is very important.
germayne: Okay, so essentially, you can see here, this is a very intuitive example, like the stock market, any kind of data that has a date that is stacked to it.
germayne: the meaning is lost if I were to shuffle them, right? Because it doesn't make sense. So what this means is that from the model perspective, or any kind of model that you're trying to model, you need some kind of information, you need some kind of mechanism.
germayne: to structure… to model the structure. So the structure needs to be taken into account by any algorithms that you are using.
germayne: Okay?
germayne: Of course, cross-sectional data is the one that we have been working on all the time.
germayne: Any kind of data, usually, if, let's say, you're thinking in terms of survey, if you're asking people questions.
germayne: Right? You're predicting people's income, right? I have a data set of 1,000 people. It doesn't really matter if I shuffle the top 5 rows with the bottom 5 rows, it doesn't really matter, because every row is independent.
germayne: the model doesn't care about the sequence, so you do not need to model the sequence into the model, right? You can, you know, if you remember the cross-validation.
germayne: that we covered, right? You could just potentially jumble and split the data up, doesn't… doesn't really… doesn't really matter, right?
germayne: I can just cut here, I can shuffle, I can, you know, do train, test, split, randomly shuffle, it doesn't matter, right? If I take 30, 70, because each of the data, anyways, they are independent, right? Doesn't really matter.
germayne: Okay? So, most of the time, when you're working with, you know, all the typical data that we have for all the supervised learning, they're actually all cross-sectional data.
germayne: And of course, from a… usually we call panel data usually is used in econometrics. Actually, it's very commonly used in econometrics. But you can think of panel data as just a, you know, a data set that has multiple variables.
germayne: that is tagged to the date. So you can see here, we have 3 stock… different stock prices, that is, with respect to the date.
germayne: Okay? So…
germayne: this just basically combines your time series and your cross-sectional data, where now you have multiple, multiple, you know, you can think of them as a cross-sectional plus time series, where, you know, every row has a time series, and then maybe I have another column that tries to break them into different portions.
germayne: Right? Another example you can think of is something like your sales data as well. Because if, let's say, you are working on a sales data, you're analyzing a sales data, you wouldn't have just one sales value, right? You might have sales value of all the different stores in Singapore, right? So then that's an example of a panel data.
germayne: Okay, so, you know, here there's a very general, general, guideline of, like, the type of data types, but I think in general, in general, the rule of thumb here is that if your data type has some kind of timestamp.
germayne: Or some kind of date. And, you know, this date is actually very important, right? In the sense of, like, without the date, there's no context, then you know that you're working with a time series data.
germayne: Okay? So, for cross-sectional data, I think that's really a very common data type. Things like your, you know, every individual independent instance, they're all independently collected, then they are basically just cross-sectional data.
germayne: Then now, for panel data, in this context, right, right, I'm not going to econometrics, but in this context, for the panel data, what we are just basically saying here is that you have a time series data set that essentially has some kind of
germayne: categorization that allows you to break them into different portions. So one example, like what I mentioned, is things like your, you know, you have multiple sales data, for example, you have a date.
germayne: Oh, wait, let me go to…
germayne: So, for example, you have something like your, your, your, you have a date.
germayne: Then you have something like your sails.
germayne: And then you have something like, another, another categorical variable that breaks down, maybe like the store.
germayne: And then maybe something like the country.
germayne: Right? Something like country. So, essentially, you have some kind of panel data with multiple time series data, right? And of course, there's a lot of… I mean, that will actually be a very common data type when you work with time series.
germayne: Okay, I'll stop here first.
germayne: Anybody has any questions for me so far, just for the warm-up of time series?
germayne: quite, quite straightforward, right? I'm sure everyone
germayne: will have seen this data. And because, right, the property of time series, when we try to use algorithm to predict time series, you have to treat them differently. You can't… you can't take whatever that you have learned so far and then just apply it, right? It will not work.
germayne: Okay? There will be a lot of issues, because time series, you have to think of a way to model the structure.
germayne: Okay, I think, I think, before I go on and talk about visualization, actually, I… I have provided this reference here. So essentially, a lot of, a lot of content today that will be covered can easily be found in this textbook by Rob Hyman, right?
germayne: He is a very established professor from Australia, and I have always been using his material when I was doing time series.
germayne: as a data scientist, okay? And why is he actually a big deal? He actually wrote this book back then, and a lot of this book is actually written in R programming.
germayne: But again, right, like what I mentioned, the code doesn't really matter. But the important takeaway is that
germayne: he's actually involved with this, time series competition called M Competition, so you can… I added the link here. So, essentially, the Mark Rida Keyes competition, they have been doing this competition for many years, essentially from M1 all the way to M5.
germayne: So essentially, this competition is a very respectable competition where they would release a lot of time series data, like 45,000 time series data, for example. I think Walmart did it many years back for M5.
germayne: Walmart released a lot of time series data, and it's actually a sort of like an open competition where the brightest people will come and compete.
germayne: right, they'll write an algo and try to see whether they can forecast it better. And I think he created a lot of methodology and algorithms, which you will see later, and it's all… it's basically all from him, right? So basically, he's Professor Rob. I think he's in Monash University. So he's quite a big deal, and I think a lot of
germayne: materials here, if you are super keen, right, and you know, you don't feel very satisfied, I really highly recommend the book.
germayne: Okay? The book will be a good starting… the book will be a good starting point. And of course, the book is free, so I gave the… I gave the link here. So this is a second edition. They actually have the third edition already, but at least a lot of the materials that I based on, I think the second edition will be good enough, and it's actually free online, so you can… you can refer to it. So none of the things that we thought today
germayne: sorry, rather, most of the things that we talked today, 99% of it all can be found in the book, and I will reference to you which chapter you can read on.
germayne: Okay? So, the idea here is that, of course.
germayne: For… for the… wait, how many people do I have today?
germayne: I have 41, so at least for the, for the, you know, excluding me.
germayne: Elvin and Soon, right? The remaining 38 of you guys, if you are very keen in time series, right, and you feel like you need some kind of literature to, you know, to ensure that you're doing the right thing, I would highly recommend this book. So, this is, of course, in your…
germayne: In your… what do you call that? In your notes.
germayne: Okay? All good.
germayne: Okay, so I think we are just going to, you know, just digress a bit. I know we're not going to do the modeling yet, but I think this is just an introduction, again, back to your data visualization. I think it's more relevant for… for how do you visualize your time series data.
germayne: And… and… I would say it's actually more relevant for, like, Module 1, right? If you think about your EDA.
germayne: So, of course, you're, you know, visualizing time series here, they are just some very basic
germayne: advice, in terms of, like, okay, I think one way to, you know, when you want to look at time series is, of course, to look at the trends, you know, understand the seasonality, see if there are any anomalies, and then you want to communicate with your stakeholders. Of course, this is a very, very generic advice.
germayne: But I think the end of the day, the advice still follows, right? The general direction that I always mention to you guys.
germayne: When you are doing data visualization, always remember what is the problem statement that you're solving, right?
germayne: When you're working with data, you are not doing something for the sake of doing something, right?
germayne: All of the mechanisms, all of the tools that was taught, they are a way for you to
germayne: you know, bring some kind of insight from the data, but I think one thing that a lot of people, when they start to do data analytics, is that they forget what is the problem statement. So always try to understand what is exactly the problem that you're trying to answer, right? So this, of course, will make sense when you have the relevant question.
germayne: Right? There is either from business.
germayne: or it's actually driven by you and your team, right? So, of course, you want to understand trends if, let's say, the question is that, how will I understand the overall pattern for the last X years, X months, from a time series data? Then, then, looking at trends is relevant, right?
germayne: But I'm not saying here that, oh, you know, if you identify trends, your first step in your EDA is that, okay, I'll just look at the trend. Looking at a trend is meaningless if it doesn't answer your question, right? Same thing for seasonality and stuff.
germayne: Okay, so we'll do this a bit more in the notebook. There will be a section for visualization.
germayne: But I'll spend some time talking about the metrics. Sorry, about the decomposition.
germayne: Okay, so this is… this is just a small portion, just another portion about talking about time series decomposition. So actually, you can find this, again, in the textbook. This is actually chapter 6, if I remember correctly, I think.
germayne: I believe this is chapter 6. Yeah, so this is chapter 6. So in chapter 6, you actually see about time series decomposition, right? So we'll spend some time talking about time series decomposition. It essentially is just a methodology where, given a time series, can I actually deconstruct the time series into different portions? Can I actually break the time series up?
germayne: Okay? And of course, there are many, in the book, right, you'll see that they actually introduce many, many new methods, right? There's the STL, there's the classical one, which we are going to teach the classical one, and of course, there's also, like, the… the… I believe there's a few other methods.
germayne: That is actually created by different people. There's also the X11 that is actually created from the Bank of
germayne: sorry, sorry, seeds. Later on, you'll see, in seeds, actually, I think it's created by the Bank of Spain. So it's actually very, very smart people. Oh, by the way, right, time series has been around for very long. So, the classical decomposition that we are talking about came from 1920, right? So you can see it's actually very, very long ago.
germayne: So the motivation for time series decomposition is that if, let's say, for example, you want to, you know… there's two schools of thoughts.
germayne: Either you want to forecast.
germayne: And the rationale later will explain. Or, you just want to do some analysis, and of course, decomposition will help you understand your time series clearer, right, rather than just do it visually. So this is a… this is a more quantitative method.
germayne: And the idea here is that if you have a time series, if you can see that your time series… your time series is basically, you can think of it, at least from the classical method, that it can actually be decomposed mathematically into three portions, and they're just additive.
germayne: You essentially have the trend.
germayne: the seasonal component, as well as what we call the residual, which is anything outside of your seasonal and trend. And if you were to just add these three together.
germayne: you're just going to get back your observation… your observed time series. So the idea here is that, okay, maybe if you just want to isolate and understand the trend, then I can just look at the trend. And if I just want to capture what is the seasonality.
germayne: you know, the recurring cycle in the data, I'll just do it, right? And of course, the remainder will be things that will be outside of your trend and seasonal. So that is how the classical method actually came about.
germayne: Okay? But of course, in practice, you can see the textbook, they say that people no longer use the classical method, but from a pedagogy perspective, I think it's still important to have the intuition of how it's actually done.
germayne: Okay, so for the time series decomposition, if you again follow the textbook, right, they actually introduce two methods, right? One is actually called the, you know, identifying if your time series is additive, right? And… or identifying if your time series is multiplicative.
germayne: So I'll show some visualization later on how do you actually identify that, but the idea here is that the additive just basically means that the variation, the seasonal variation, is actually independent. It doesn't grow across time, right? I'll show some…
germayne: image later. For multiplicative, basically, as time goes past, the seasonal variation starts to become larger and larger, so it's actually proportional to the trend.
germayne: Okay? And…
germayne: why is it important for you, from a classical decomposition mechanism, why is it important to identify the additive or the multiplicative? It's because this affects how the methodology to break them down, right, it will affect the method they will be using to break them down.
germayne: Okay?
germayne: Okay, of course, there's also a transformation called BoxCorps. We didn't… we didn't… we didn't really go very deep about it, right? I… I think in the class, oh.
germayne: I think in the class, during linear regression, we talked a bit about the log-log. If you guys remember, right, we talked about the interpretation, the log-log.
germayne: regular log. So actually, the interesting thing is that in the textbook, right, you also see about boxcards, because it's coming from a perspective of statistical inference, right, statistical model. And boxcards is basically a general mechanism to transform your data, and log is actually one of the transformation parameters that boxcards can do.
germayne: So essentially here, the idea is that Again, right, nothing…
germayne: Nothing new here, nothing secretive here. If you have a multiplicative model, you can actually perform a transformation to transform them back to additive, if you want to use the additive. May or may not work, right? But you have to look at it visually.
germayne: Okay, so this is just a classical method, don't really have to remember.
germayne: Right, we'll just walk through to get some intuition.
germayne: So I gave some additional example here. So basically, you can see that, between the left and right, right, you notice that the cycle is actually consistent across time, right? You can see, right, the cycle doesn't grow. So this is what we call additive.
germayne: On the right-hand side, you notice that the cycle starts to become very… the variation of the cycle starts to become more and more and more and more. So essentially, you can see that it follows the trend, right, as time goes past.
germayne: the variation gets more and more. So what this means is that this is actually a very good sign that it's a multiplicative, you know, you have to use a multiplicative method rather than an additive method.
germayne: Okay, and this is, of course, some example data. You can see on the left-hand side, what do you guys think this is from the left-hand side, based on what you guys… what I have shown in the previous slide.
germayne: what is the time series on the left? I think this is the monthly demand in millions. So what? This is a very… what kind of…
Phillip Tan Lip Teck: Particularly.
germayne: multiplicative, exactly, because you can see that the cycle starts to become, you know, stronger and stronger and stronger across time, right? And of course, similarly, on the right-hand side, you can see that this is an example that the trend is actually… the whole time series is actually additive.
germayne: Right, you can see that the variation did not really change that much, at least compared to the left… the left-hand side.
germayne: Okay, so don't really need to remember this, Textbook Chapter 6 has the exact full algorithm in there, but the mechanism here is that they actually use a… something called moving average, right, moving rolling average. Anybody knows what is a moving average? Anybody here does stock analysis, do technical analysis on stocks.
germayne: Anybody knows what is the moving average?
germayne: I see some heads nodding.
germayne: Who knows?
germayne: Fit it.
Zac Ang: average over time.
Phillip Tan Lip Teck: I wish I would know that.
germayne: Correct. Exactly, exactly, exactly. So you actually, you guys… so it's a very common thing, right? So those of you who actually do, like, some stocks analysis, right? Essentially, you can actually smoothen the graph, right, by actually running a window. So essentially, there's a window. You run a window.
germayne: Right? And you just scan the window across all of it, and for each of the windows, you calculate the average, correct? So essentially, the outcome of it is that you will smooth the entire time series, and fun fact, that's actually how they do it in the classical method. That's actually how they use it to get the trend component. By actually running a… a…
germayne: Moving average, and by the way, the formula for moving average is something like 2K plus 1, in terms of the… the number of elements. Why? Because it needs to be odd number.
germayne: Right? It needs to be odd-numbered so that the placement of the aggregate will always be at the center.
germayne: Right? So again, in the textbook, you can see that if you go into moving average, they will just tell you that time series is defined by 2K plus 1, which is essentially… it needs to be forced to be an odd number.
germayne: Right? But, you know, if you don't really know this, it's okay. The idea here is that by scanning a window and running across the time series, right, the center index, right, if let's say you have, 3,
germayne: If there's 3, 3 data points here, you're always going to be taking the average on the center.
germayne: Right, so the center placement will take the average of the three, you scan the window to the next one, you take the center placement, you take the middle, and of course, you can choose the window to be any 2K plus 1 elements. Of course, the book go even further. If you go and read the book, take some time to read the book.
germayne: And by the way, right, the book is actually not a lot of chapters. You can easily just read it in one weekend per chapter, it's actually very fast. You will see that they also tell you, you know, even more details about the moving average. Actually, you can also do even.
germayne: Right? By doing two moving averages together. Of course, it's not important for this class, I'm not going to go into details, but the beauty of the classical approach is that you can actually see that this concept, moving average, is actually used to obtain the trend.
germayne: By smoothering out all of the cycles within the time series, actually you get a very nice trend component, right? And then what they do is, once you get the trend, you detrend the time series, which is you take Y minus T, which is like, for every item, I'm just going to detrend it. And what is the purpose of detraining it? Anybody wants to take a guess.
germayne: Why do I want to detrend at this step? What's the intuition here?
Zac Ang: Find the error.
germayne: Correct. So, by… by… I mean, partially correct. So, if you take away the trend, right, if you remember, mathematically, we said that every time series must be
germayne: a trend.
germayne: a season and the remainder noise, right? So if you take away the trend, essentially what is remaining is the seasonal component and the residual, right? So, of course, there's also a methodology to compute the seasonal component.
germayne: I'm not going to go into details here. Actually, the book has some details on how they calculate it, but the idea here is you just take the average of every seasonal peak, every seasonal frequency, you take the average, and then you center it by mining the mean. So you just zero it.
germayne: And then once you actually get the seasonal component, you finally can take the Y minus the T minus the S, and that is your residual. And of course, if it's multiplicative, then you do a division.
germayne: But you can see this is a very classical, this is a very old-school method.
germayne: what is suggested by Professor Rob is that if you, this method is actually not that popular now. I think they have other, other, other methods, but this is a method that originated from the 1920s, okay? Very, very simple, and I think what… where it helps is that it
germayne: gives you the intuition on how the decomposition works, right? So, you know, it says that it's still widely used, but he… but from his word is that he doesn't suggest this, and he suggests some of the newer methods, because there are still some drawbacks from classical decomposition methods.
germayne: So, of course, there's the STL, which is the newer method, S11, and I think this is the one that is created by the Bank of Spain.
germayne: Okay, I think I'll stop here first. I think I see that there are still some people.
germayne: lake Hong, what does that mean? Module 1 takes X days average.
germayne: What does that mean?
Lik Hong Eng: No, that's why you're asking about, movie enrichment.
Lik Hong Eng: I record it from Volume 1.
germayne: Okay, okay.
germayne: Okay, so anybody got any questions? Hey, where's the… Where's my…
germayne: Where's the picture of everyone's faces?
germayne: Wait I think I lost it.
germayne: For some reason, I cannot see everyone now.
germayne: Okay. Anybody got any question or not?
germayne: Okay, so see, here's the thing, right? Why it's helpful for me to see everyone is so that it doesn't feel like I'm talking to myself.
germayne: Okay, so I'll just continue, huh?
germayne: Okay, so I think these two we'll go through, we'll go through, in the note, I think soon we'll just… we'll go through this before we go to part 3 later on.
germayne: Okay?
germayne: Okay, soon, I'll hand it over to you.
Soon | NTU: Okay, thank you, Jumin.
Soon | NTU: Okay.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so I will have, three…
Soon | NTU: portion… three parts to cover, right? The first one is the visualization. Let me share the screen first.
Soon | NTU: There are two parts to this Jupyter Notebook session.
Soon | NTU: Okay, let me share…
Soon | NTU: Okay, so this, Jupyter Notebook is for 3.6,
Soon | NTU: And then, if you have the notebook open up, probably you can go to this outline in the VS Code.
Soon | NTU: under visualize… visualizing… time series data.
Soon | NTU: section.
Soon | NTU: Right, because, the first section, I think, is more for a lot of those,
Soon | NTU: Content which the Germaine has already covered, right?
Soon | NTU: So, for visualization of the time series data.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so we are using this, classic dataset from SKTime.
Soon | NTU: Right.
Soon | NTU: So this name… is,
Soon | NTU: all of you can see the screen, right? And also can hear my… my voice, just for,
Soon | NTU: Audio check in the, okay, so this is a very classical data set from SKTime.
Soon | NTU: This library is, created specifically for doing the time series analysis, okay? So if you look at the name, naming convention, sk time and sklearn, right?
Soon | NTU: SKTime is actually a cousin of sklearn. Okay, so the purpose is, you know, when you have already chosen a model.
Soon | NTU: to…
Soon | NTU: train it or feed it onto your data set, right? So, you will still use the usual, function call, okay, feed.
Soon | NTU: and also predict for forecasting, okay? So, we do not have to have a different function name to do the forecasting for time series data, okay? So, in a way, you make everything, like.
Soon | NTU: doing your data analysis very, consistently, you know, with what you have done also in the SKLearn, right? So, SKTime has, a lot of built-in dataset, okay, similar to what we have seen in SKLearn, okay? So, if you were to go to the
Soon | NTU: official website of the SK Learn, SK Time.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so you just, look for escape time, and then you should be able to
Soon | NTU: get this link, okay, just to want to show you how you can get more information about the… the other standard dataset, right?
Soon | NTU: If you are curious to do, data analysis of your own, you know, you can always try out the other dataset, okay, after we have, shared with you a bit about the load airline data set, right? You can apply this, whatever you learned to the other dataset as well, right? So.
Soon | NTU: And then, this is how you can load the… data set.
Soon | NTU: So this is, airline, passenger.
Soon | NTU: Dataset basically is, containing 12 years of data, monthly data. Okay, so 12 years
Soon | NTU: 12 months, so they're all together 144 data points, right? Monthly data point. And…
Soon | NTU: If you look at the, data that you have loaded from this dataset, you can see that the first period starts from 1949. Okay, so this is,
Soon | NTU: Dinging, just after the… World Touring.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so people are beginning to, free to travel, right? So, 1949, January, and then you have the number of airline passengers
Soon | NTU: in hundreds, yeah. So I think probably during those days.
Soon | NTU: not many people could afford, you know, to travel by air, right? Probably most of them do it by sea, right? So, it's only at about 100 over per month.
Soon | NTU: Right? And then… To plot the time series data, okay, we just have to call this function
Soon | NTU: data.plot. Okay, so this is a function call that you can use to
Soon | NTU: Apply onto your data set, and… Okay, so this data is, a series.
Soon | NTU: Okay, if you go to the SK
Soon | NTU: learn… no, SKTimeLibrary. Okay, so this load airline will give you a…
Soon | NTU: Pandas series, okay? So this pandas series, in order for the plot function to work right.
Soon | NTU: You have to have at least one of the columns is a time.
Soon | NTU: column.
Soon | NTU: Okay, otherwise, this plot will not know how to interpret your, your…
Soon | NTU: your series, okay? So this is how it looks like, okay? So, from the chart, What can you tell?
Soon | NTU: Okay, so… There's actually a very obvious upward trend.
Soon | NTU: This is visual by visually, you know, this is, how you do… You know.
Soon | NTU: a visual inspection of what kind of data you actually have in hand, right? Before you go into the next step, oh, I already seen that.
Soon | NTU: There is an upward trend, Right.
Soon | NTU: There is also, whoa.
Soon | NTU: What do you call this?
Phillip Tan Lip Teck: Seasonality.
Soon | NTU: Yeah?
Soon | NTU: There's a seasonality, and how is the magnitude of this seasonality its light over time?
Phillip Tan Lip Teck: I'll be creative.
Soon | NTU: Yes, yes, okay, very good. Okay, so if you know that the, seasonality, okay, right from the beginning is only at a very small, you know, magnitude, and then slowly the magnitude increases over time, okay? So, you roughly can tell, oh, you know, probably the…
Soon | NTU: we won't be using additive, the time CV decomposition model, but instead, it will be more applicable to use, multiplicative
Soon | NTU: Right? Model to decompose your, the component of your time series data, actually. I think this visual inspection is
Soon | NTU: It will give you a very good head start, you know, at least to know, oh, what kind of data you are, you know, going to have for the next step, right?
Soon | NTU: And then… So just so you know, apart from the trend, you also have this season.
Soon | NTU: Third component, of course, is the remaining, the irregular component, which we usually call the residual, okay? So the second part is, okay, this one will…
Soon | NTU: give us a rough idea, oh, there's an upward trend. And the seasonal plot will also give us an idea. Okay, so this will give us a unique value of the year.
Soon | NTU: Okay, because otherwise you will have a repeated number of years, and we only want to have the unique years
Soon | NTU: Which is basically the area of town numbers.
Soon | NTU: Right?
Soon | NTU: And then, when we plot it, Using the, metro plot function.
Soon | NTU: You will have this seasonal plot.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so what can you tell from this, plot?
Soon | NTU: So this is basically a chart, right?
Soon | NTU: Each line will represent the 12 months of data, monthly data point, okay?
Soon | NTU: In separate line.
Soon | NTU: Mike, this is, 1949.
Soon | NTU: 50, 51, and so on. Okay, so the last line is orange, so it's 1960.
Soon | NTU: Okay.
Soon | NTU: I think all of us were… were not born yet, like, okay? So, 1960, so you have a curve here at the line here, okay? So what does this
Soon | NTU: Chuck tell us.
Soon | NTU: Can someone want to try?
Hitesh shah: June and…
Soon | NTU: I think this is very important to know how to at least visually interpret your time series, because time series data set can be very complicated because of the different components hidden in the data.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so by, using this…
Soon | NTU: divide and conquer, right? You first sift out the, seasonal component, okay? So, this is the…
Soon | NTU: thing that we are doing now by using this seasonal plot, okay? So from this chart, what can you tell?
Hitesh shah: June and July has the maximum passengers each year.
Soon | NTU: Sorry? Did I…
Hitesh shah: June and July.
Hitesh shah: And August are the seasonal period where you have more, more traffic in,
Soon | NTU: Oh, yes. Oh, yeah, yeah. That's a very good, observation. Yeah, very good, so…
Hitesh shah: November is the lowest point.
Hitesh shah: November is the lowest point every year.
Soon | NTU: Mmm.
Hitesh shah: So any… any maintenance work and all, you can do on November.
Soon | NTU: Okay.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so, yes, I think there is, some seasonal, I would say, Seasonality detected within this
Soon | NTU: In fact, it's in this July and August months.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so you can see, for each of this year, even right from the first 1949, when this, the data provider was IATA, I-A-T-A, okay, so they have, already
Soon | NTU: The data, okay?
Soon | NTU: Visually, it's telling us that it's some kind of a seasonal
Soon | NTU: pick at the July and August period, okay? So, the first question I ask myself when I see this, is this…
Soon | NTU: Is this data set?
Soon | NTU: Any, any data point from, Asia?
Soon | NTU: Okay, because… Usually, our travel pattern is slightly different from the Western European country, you know, the,
Soon | NTU: the northern hemisphere. Okay, because our… we don't usually have a summer pig premise season at
Soon | NTU: This is a summer, right? Okay? Now.
Soon | NTU: Yes, there is a peak in July and August.
Soon | NTU: Right, in all the year, Okay? And also, The downward trend in the… winter season.
Soon | NTU: Right? We don't have winter in Singapore, right? Anyway, we wouldn't have this kind of, like, air, so-called travel.
Soon | NTU: for this part of Singapore, right? So…
Soon | NTU: Right? Okay, so from this chart, you know there is some kind of a seasonality hidden in our data set, right? And then.
Soon | NTU: No.
Soon | NTU: why not we plot the same data instead of yearly across all the different months, right? Now, why not we plot the same, months of data
Soon | NTU: For each of the year, in the same Supply.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so in Seabond, we have this,
Soon | NTU: Okay, before that, we need to do some conversion, right? Okay? Because Seabourn need to have owed.
Soon | NTU: Date inside your data frame.
Soon | NTU: Okay, in order for your… your next, code to work.
Soon | NTU: Right?
Soon | NTU: This Yvonne is very particular about this. Now, of course, you can test it out. If I don't do the conversion, if I don't have a date and a month and year in my data frame, what will happen?
Soon | NTU: Okay, you can… you can try it out, okay, but I won't… I won't want to do it here, okay, just for you to explore, right? Now, there is a facade grid function, this class, for us to plot out all the months, the variation of
Soon | NTU: Across the year, on the same subplot.
Soon | NTU: Okay.
Soon | NTU: And then, this is the result. Okay, let me… Make it smaller.
Soon | NTU: Okay, now, based on this subplot, right, there will be also a very consistent, you know, observation in that
Soon | NTU: There is a… the rate of, increase of the passenger count. Now, the vertical axis
Soon | NTU: Right? It's a passenger count.
Soon | NTU: It's only in the hundreds, huh?
Soon | NTU: You only, like, now… nowadays, you know, the air travel pattern is so… Drastically different from…
Soon | NTU: in the night… in the… in the 50s, right? So now, you… by looking at the upper limit of the vertical axis, you'll know, right, from 100 all the way to 600 in July.
Soon | NTU: 100 to 600, okay? This is only… 500.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so the highest number is 600 in July and August, okay? So, this means
Soon | NTU: Okay? For the same month of July, if I gotta go
Soon | NTU: year by year, okay? So the rate of increase is the highest in the month of July and August.
Soon | NTU: So this is how we interpret the… First subgrid in,
Soon | NTU: CBOM, the plotting library. Okay, I think… I think this is a very, very useful chart. It may not be for time series, but you can also apply to… for other
Soon | NTU: use cases, right? But predominantly for time series analysis, okay?
Hitesh shah: If you want the x-axis to be same, we can do that.
Soon | NTU: I'm sorry?
Hitesh shah: If you want the x-axis to be same, can we do that? Because… For each month, it's… it's…
Soon | NTU: the x-axis…
Hitesh shah: to be same, so it starts from the same, so some plotting is at 200 scale, and another plotting is at 150, so I just wanted to…
Soon | NTU: Do you mean to share the same skill?
Hitesh shah: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Soon | NTU: X or Y.
Hitesh shah: XX, all of, all the graph, because it might be a little misleading if you are comparing different ones. Someone is starting at.
Soon | NTU: The x-axis is already the same.
Hitesh shah: No, sorry, why, why?
Soon | NTU: AI, okay? So, no. In Seabone.
Soon | NTU: You can actually change this to… This is…
Soon | NTU: not shareY, yeah, this is shareY. Okay, so if you do not want the different line plot to have a different scale, right, you can use this to set this to true.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so all the sign plot will now share the same, Duh, but…
Soon | NTU: The, the, the vertical, axis.
Hitesh shah: Thank you.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so this is how… you can see this is the slippers in July and August.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so by default, the y-axis, the horizontal axis, sorry, the axis, horizontal axis is the same
Soon | NTU: Yeah, for all the line plot.
Soon | NTU: This is elected.
Soon | NTU: Right?
Soon | NTU: Okay, let He put this tube.
Soon | NTU: Okay? So, now.
Soon | NTU: For time series analysis, there's one very important concept, is this thing called a lag. So just now, we have come to the lesson, Germaine has explained to you, right?
Soon | NTU: Is that… what's the concept of lag? Okay, so basically, the assumption is, right, in order for this time series data to be useful for your forecasting,
Soon | NTU: for prediction, right? To…
Soon | NTU: a value add to your business planning, okay? There must be some kind of a correlation
Soon | NTU: Between, the data today and the data yesterday.
Soon | NTU: Okay.
Soon | NTU: So that is a very, very basic assumption, okay? Now, if there is no correlation between what is happening today versus tomorrow, okay? Basically, there is no correlation, and it will be quite difficult for you to predict what is going to happen in the future.
Soon | NTU: Right? So, this is one of the very important concepts. Now, in order for us to know whether this lag, right.
Soon | NTU: Right.
Soon | NTU: How… if something happened today, If my stock price is, like, this $1,000, okay?
Soon | NTU: How it's gonna affect the surprises in the next
Soon | NTU: few periods, how long would that take? Okay, so this one basically will tell you
Soon | NTU: Black one means one period.
Soon | NTU: before, okay? If this is the monthly data we have in the airline passenger data set, right? So, this leg plot, basically.
Soon | NTU: just a function call, okay? So this basically is plotting the Y current
Soon | NTU: At the current time, versus the why.
Soon | NTU: Just one period of the previous month.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so, okay, so in this case, this is, forward the next month, again.
Soon | NTU: So we can see that there is a positive
Soon | NTU: slope, right, in the log… in the data. Okay, so this is a very, good.
Soon | NTU: Okay? Signal to you that, oh, there is a key…
Soon | NTU: correlation between the data point that we see yesterday versus the data point we have today in our data, right, in our air passenger data set, okay? So.
Soon | NTU: If there's no correlation, then there's nothing for us to do, right? Okay? So, this correlation, autocorrelation, will…
Soon | NTU: compute, okay, what is actually that correlation at each of these legs, t versus t plus 1, and t versus t plus 2, and so on, okay? So, you will have this formula, and then you sum it up, okay, because, of course, we are not going to go through the mathematics, but
Soon | NTU: We have this ACFN, plot ACF,
Soon | NTU: function from the sets model.
Soon | NTU: Right, because these, functions are already available, so you…
Soon | NTU: SKLearn will not need to reinvent the wheel and create another version of the function to do the same thing, right? Okay? So, ACF function.
Soon | NTU: Fitting in our line… airline passenger dataset.
Soon | NTU: Flogged with a lack of from 1 to 60, okay? So these are the value we have.
Soon | NTU: Okay? And then, of course, you can't really tell, hey, you know, how does this look like? But the plot…
Soon | NTU: ACF function will give you a Picture like this.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so this one will tell you
Soon | NTU: Okay, when you do your time series analysis.
Soon | NTU: if you inspect the ACF block, they visually, right? So, automatically, you have, alpha 0.05 means the confidence
Soon | NTU: interval automatically is set, default to 95% confident, because our fund is, significance level at, 5%.
Soon | NTU: Okay?
Soon | NTU: So… Any dot that you see outside of this confidence, interval.
Soon | NTU: She need for good.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so you can see your… ACF.
Soon | NTU: It's showing that your data point has, autocorrelation up to a lack of, About 12, 13?
Soon | NTU: Okay? Before it becomes insignificant.
Soon | NTU: Statistically insignificant, okay?
Soon | NTU: So this is, how we make use of the ACF plot tool.
Soon | NTU: you know, visually inspect, okay, beyond just now our trend, and also the season, okay? So there are a lot of,
Soon | NTU: charts that are available for us to do time series analysis, okay? Now.
Soon | NTU: So, we have gone through the, the…
Soon | NTU: analysis on the seasonality, and also the trend, okay? And then, how about the third component is the white noise.
Soon | NTU: White noise is actually the repeater. Okay, so in time series analysis, right.
Soon | NTU: In addition, for us to decompose the original time series data into the respective component, right?
Soon | NTU: One of the components One of the core components of time series data.
Soon | NTU: Is this thing called the… The… we call it the residue, or the irregular component.
Soon | NTU: Okay, the other one is seasonality, and then trend.
Soon | NTU: Right, remember our additive or multiplicative, The model, right?
Soon | NTU: the T, S, and R.
Soon | NTU: So the TSR, this is the R we are referring to, right? So now, if you look at the mean and the variance of our
Soon | NTU: A-line data set is still now. We have a mean of 280 and a variance of 14.
Soon | NTU: Thousand.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so now, with this… series.
Soon | NTU: with this data, right? Okay, so we have created one function here, Okay, so basically…
Soon | NTU: is for you to… you don't have to do this manually, okay, because there are a lot of built-in
Soon | NTU: statistical tests available in the SK Time Library for you to determine whether your remaining, after you have taken away the trend and the seasonality, whether the remaining is a residual
Soon | NTU: Okay.
Soon | NTU: It is similar to what you have done in your regression, Linear regression, right?
Soon | NTU: You want to… Form a linear regression equation.
Soon | NTU: To explain as much variation in the data as possible.
Soon | NTU: Right? If you have 80%, well… That's very good. Remaining 20%.
Soon | NTU: derision is.
Soon | NTU: not explain, okay? So you accept 80% as, good enough, okay? So the remaining 20% is the, something that you are not able to
Soon | NTU: Let's say, put in additional feature to explain why there is an additional 20% out there.
Soon | NTU: cannot be explained using my equation, okay? So, likewise in
Soon | NTU: time series decomposition. So, after we have taken out the trend, Seasonality.
Soon | NTU: what remains is the residue, right, the white noise, and this function basically is telling you, right, based on your ACF,
Soon | NTU: Based on these statistical tests, Right? This is, Levine.
Soon | NTU: Sapiro, Right.
Soon | NTU: Now, all these are statistical tests for you to Check, right, whether you're…
Soon | NTU: p-value is small enough to reject your null hypothesis.
Soon | NTU: Okay? Now, if any of these Fail.
Soon | NTU: Right. That means there is still some residue, okay? You did not have a complete model, time series model, that you have found, okay, to explain 80% of the
Soon | NTU: Time series component in your dataset.
Soon | NTU: Okay. Let's just something indoor.
Soon | NTU: in a residual, okay? So you can do better, okay? So, this function call have to return true in order you can
Soon | NTU: You know, are confident in the model that you have found.
Soon | NTU: I will explain to you, you know, how the models are configured later, right? So this is a very good, convenient function for you to test out. Now, as to what are all these,
Soon | NTU: Statistical test, right?
Soon | NTU: We have, prepared some tests here, okay? So, just to…
Soon | NTU: Tell you, which are the…
Soon | NTU: What are the respective, null hypotheses in green?
Soon | NTU: Okay, so the alternative hypothesis is in yellow.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so for… Levine, it is to check for constant variants, okay? So, You have to have At least…
Soon | NTU: Right.
Soon | NTU: So, if this is… Greater than alpha, that means your…
Soon | NTU: you don't reject your null hypothesis, okay? So… everything is…
Soon | NTU: constant. Okay, so that is very good. Okay, so this,
Soon | NTU: 6, statistical tests. There could be more than just these tests, but I would say these 6 tests are…
Soon | NTU: very, commonly used, right? As you go on to the next, few boxes, you will also come across a lot of, DuneBox tasks, and also, especially this augmented
Soon | NTU: Dickie Fullert has rank.
Soon | NTU: So, we'll come to this again, as we go through the code.
Soon | NTU: Right?
Soon | NTU: Any questions, from anyone?
Soon | NTU: Okay, so if not, I will go through the next section on the time series decomposition.
Soon | NTU: Before we go back to the, the, the, the lesson, right?
Soon | NTU: So, I think this is a very short section. So, for time series decomposition, so basically we have, basically two methods, right? Additive or multiplicative, and we have already seen in your seasonal decomposition just now.
Soon | NTU: Right? We know there is a seasonality inside, okay? And also, it… seasonality… The magnitude, okay?
Soon | NTU: seem to have… seem to increase over time, okay? So now…
Soon | NTU: This is the function that you can use to
Soon | NTU: applying onto your time series data set, okay? First, we look at how the additive,
Soon | NTU: Model will look like, okay?
Soon | NTU: Okay, so this is the… Original data set?
Soon | NTU: And then this is a train.
Soon | NTU: Season, and then this is the residue.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so this residue, if you look at this visually, you know.
Soon | NTU: That is… seem to be… have a lot of,
Soon | NTU: The variance is a bit… Changing.
Soon | NTU: Right.
Soon | NTU: This is the mean.
Soon | NTU: This is the center line, and you can see
Soon | NTU: Across… over time, the variants seem to be, you know, Oscillating up and down.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so this is additive.
Soon | NTU: time series model. How about If you change this model type to multiplicative, Are we getting better?
Soon | NTU: Right.
Soon | NTU: We still see the same original data set, trend, and seasonality.
Soon | NTU: Right? But now, if you look at the residue, right.
Soon | NTU: Right? It is going at a very, it's constant.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so it's…
Soon | NTU: suggests to us that, oh, multiplicative time series decomposition seem to work better than the additive,
Soon | NTU: More of the time.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so as you can see, time series analysis basically is focusing a lot of the concept, right? But the actual coding, right? We basically just call a function and
Soon | NTU: And then plot. And basically, this is what you get.
Soon | NTU: You know, so you do not need to go through a lot of, you know, manual coding. Of course, you need to have this in hand.
Soon | NTU: Okay? And then to check…
Soon | NTU: when you're doing your coding, if the p-value is 0.55, you know, what is the indication, what's the meaning, right? So this one, we always need to go through this during the time series analysis.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so this, what we have for the, time series decomposition.
Soon | NTU: Okay, let me see where I do have…
Soon | NTU: Okay, so for the part 3, right, right, probably we will continue after the break.
Soon | NTU: Is it? Do you mean?
Soon | NTU: Over to you.
germayne: Okay, let's… let's take 10 minutes lah. Let's take 10 minutes, right?
germayne: Okay, we come back at 8.23.
germayne: Hmm.
germayne: Slacker?
germayne: 2.23 back to me.
germayne: Lee, can you bring the fan in? It's very hot.
germayne: Oh.
germayne: Delta.
AU YANG TAR ben: Jamin, y'all on mute.
germayne: Oh, sorry.
AU YANG TAR ben: These kids…
germayne: Okay, so, hope, hope you guys are starting to come back already.
germayne: Okay, I will… I will start in the minutes' time.
germayne: Okay, so we… we still have… two sections.
germayne: So, yeah, I think we should be able to cover them.
germayne: So, hope you guys are recharged from your bio break.
germayne: Okay, so we are starting to go back to the prediction part.
germayne: Okay, I will, I will, I will continue.
germayne: Okay, so I think for the… for the first part of the…
germayne: module, we talk a bit about the motivations behind time series, and… as well as some visualization. I think there were some statistical tests shown. I… I think my honest opinion is I don't think you guys need to worry too much about
germayne: about all of the statistical tests, I think there are… there are a few notable ones that are important, but I don't think you need to know all of it, right? And… and I think… I think generally speaking, if the goal is for predictive.
germayne: the statistical test is not that… it's not that… it's not that critical. But there is some that we will need to talk about later on, but… but before that.
germayne: What we want to talk about for this segment, before we go into the prediction, is just to focus a bit back to the validation portion, right?
germayne: So, at this point in time, you guys should already be very familiar with what validation is, especially if you guys have already done the Kaggle, right? If you guys are still ongoing, you guys should have an idea of why I keep emphasizing validation is very important, okay?
germayne: I… I would say it's super, super, super, super, super important, because
germayne: I… I've seen data scientists that cannot even do proper validation, and… and…
germayne: That basically just means that when you design systems, you are just going to have a lot of issues because you are not able to correctly assess if the model that you are building is actually working.
germayne: Okay, so now, for the context, right, we are working on time series data. So what we want to introduce here again, right, is that there's this, technique for cross-validation.
germayne: nothing has fundamentally changed, right? There's just going to be a few tweaks to it. And of course, in the textbook, the textbook also talks about this. But forget the textbook, right? The point is that
germayne: What you're looking here is essentially what we call the walk-forward
germayne: validation. So why is it called working forward?
germayne: The concept is actually very simple, right? The… you will see later on, our goal is to always make a prediction for a certain number of horizons. In this example, obviously, what we are looking at is the horizon is equals to 1.
germayne: So when I say horizon equals to 1, it means that given some kind of input data, I'm interested to make a prediction, right, for a time horizon of plus 1, which is, like.
germayne: Assuming I have T number of data, X1 to XT, right?
germayne: So with T sequence of data, I want to make a prediction at T plus 1, which means the future time step 1 horizon. So you'll notice here that in this illustration, we're actually illustrating what is known as the walk-forward variation. And the idea is very simple, right? The idea is actually very simple.
germayne: Now, one of the definitions we have mentioned is that because time series data is structural, you need to ensure that the structure is intact, right? And I think now it becomes even clearer why is it that when some of you guys were presenting any
germayne: machine learning models on time series prediction, you're talking about investing. It is super important to make sure you get this validation right.
germayne: Imagine if I were to tell you that I made a model, and then I made a prediction in 2026, 5th of March. You wouldn't care, right? Because it's 5th of March. Agree? If I say that I have a very good model, perfect investment for the 5th of March, would you care? You wouldn't care.
germayne: However, if I tell you that the model has only knowledge before the 5th of March, then that's a very, very different story. So what this essentially means is that if you look at the blue part, it's actually just saying that your train data… and again, right, this is just a rule of thumb.
germayne: You can have many different variants, but the idea is that, because the whole sequence of data needs to be in the training data.
germayne: You cannot backtest something in the past.
germayne: you always have to backtest something in the future, right? So notice that the red dot basically just means that we train a model up to time step t, we make a prediction at t plus 1.
germayne: You want, you can train a model at time step t plus 1, make a forecast at t plus 2. So essentially, all these data are data sets that you have the target labels, you have the available answer to it, but what you are trying to do is you're artificially training across different models, so you have 1, 2, but I don't know how many models is this, let's assume this is, like, 20 models.
germayne: But essentially, what you're trying to test, right, very similar to your K4 here, is that you're trying to average across different steps, different models, where the goal is that the model is only exposed to a limited data set, and aimed to forecast in the future, right? And you notice that here, we are just trying to assess the model for
germayne: a horizon of one. Of course, if your model… if you're interested in predicting multiple steps ahead, of course, there's a challenge in that, but the point is that you can easily adapt this methodology to any horizon
germayne: scheme for your inference, right? But the idea here is that you're always doing a forward prediction. You're not always… you're not predicting backwards. And it's very important that you limit access to the training data that the model has, right? Hence, we are doing this. Now, I want to ask you guys a question, right?
germayne: Does this apply for your cross-sectional data?
germayne: I want to ask you guys this. So, now I'm introducing this split, right?
germayne: Can I do this for cross-sectional data?
Zac Ang: Yes.
germayne: Okay, I think Zach has participated way too many times. Okay, I'll give other… I want to answer. Okay, so… the answer is yes, but why? Why? Who knows why?
germayne: So, why I can use this for cross-sectional data? Any intuition?
Low Keng Teck, Noel: I thought that's the purpose of machine learning, right? Because you want to be able to have some sort of
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Go for exam, so… Somewhere that can, you know, test out whether you know or don't know.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: I mean, that's interesting because you are doing machine learning, so you want to do a way of… you want some data to prove that you really know what you know, right?
germayne: Not wrong also, not wrong also, I think, I think it's.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: So I don't… yeah, that's why I don't get it, like, you know, when you say intuitive, what other reasons is that? Because the main reason is the objective.
germayne: Hmm.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: So, unless it's something else, I don't know, I'm not sure.
germayne: not… that's why I say… that's why I say the answer not… not wrong also. So the takeaway here is that you can definitely apply this in whatever that we have talked previously. So you can also do your K4, right? You can also do your train test split. You can also apply it in a manner that is in the future. And the rationale, but the important here is that the rationale, right.
germayne: is because it highly depends on what is your model going to be deployed for, right? And I mentioned to you guys, if, let's say, your objective is
germayne: you envision that your model is always going to make a prediction for the next 1-2 weeks, then obviously you want to test it for a prediction performance for the next 1-2 weeks of worth of data, right? And in that case, you're still following the same methodology where you're splitting the data set across time.
germayne: Okay? But the takeaway is that for time series.
germayne: sorry, for cross-sectional data, you can and you can… it depends whether your problem statement allows that. You can also don't split across time if you are very confident, let's say, in the resEO flat data, right, in the resio flat data. If you are very confident that time factor
germayne: does not matter, which, again, might not be a true hypothesis, right? But if you are very confident, let's say for the ratio flat data, that time is not important, then the split will not be based on time.
germayne: Which is why, if you look at your test data in the Kaga dataset, actually, there's a mix of housing data that is actually from the past, right?
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Oh, yeah.
germayne: It doesn't matter. In that case, we assume that time doesn't matter. But of course, in reality, you might want to make it harder in a sense whereby you want to test it against time. So you might want to split with the time
germayne: in the future for your validation or your test set, okay? But you see, right, the idea here is that
germayne: there's no right or wrong answer for machine learning. It's not like, oh, you know, Jamin says this. I don't… it's not because I… it's because I came from a perspective
germayne: I did a lot of time series, I did a lot of Kaggle, and then later on, when I designed my machine learning models in my company, right, in GoJack, I decided that I think
germayne: especially our models are retrained automatically, right? The models are getting retrained every week, automatically deployed. Nobody has to do anything, right?
germayne: And the idea here is that I wanted to test it for the next one week, because I know that the model will be exposed for the next one week, right? So I need to know whether it's able to be robust enough for the next one week. So I chose to have a test data that is split in the future.
germayne: Okay? But the, the, the, you notice the rule of thumb here is actually very simple. Rule of thumb, right, generally speaking, is there's just only a few rules of thumb. Number one.
germayne: you want to ensure that what you're validating and what you're testing is very close to what you expect your model to be doing in the future. That's a very simple rule of thumb. Second rule of thumb is.
germayne: you want to ensure that your validation and your test and whatever is not in a way that has exposed the answer that you have used to train your model. And with this too simple a rule of thumb, right?
germayne: If you follow these two rules of thumb, then generally speaking, you shouldn't be doing anything wrong. Okay? Sounds very simple, right? But I can tell you a lot of data scientists make this mistake.
germayne: Okay? But anyways, for this, right, time series is compulsory. You have to do this, notation, you have to do this, right? And of course, in this example, there are many ways to do it, but rule of thumb here is you're always keeping a sequence of data, and you're predicting the next horizon. And here, we are trying to do it many times.
germayne: What's the rationale? Again, similar to K4. If you just do it once, you might be lucky. Maybe this horizon or this horizon is easy to predict. So what you want to do is you want to test it across many horizons, correct? And then you take the average.
germayne: Right? To make it more robust. If, let's say, out of these 20 timestamps, your machine learning model for investment is always giving you positive return, maybe you can really know that it works. You get what I mean, right?
germayne: Well, you know, and you can even test it further, you can, like, you know, do it in the uncertain, timeline, you know, if you guys remember, last year, April, Terrif was announced, right?
germayne: So, if you want to test it, oh man, maybe I test it when things are uncertain. You don't go and test it when things are certain, right? So, there are many mechanisms, there's no right or wrong answer, but the idea here is that you want to give yourself enough confidence to know that your model works.
germayne: Okay? I think that's the rule of thumb here. Now, I think you guys were saying, can I apply it to Kaggle? In this context, for Kaggle, I would say no, because in your test data, it's done in a way where I did not split it in time. If I were to split it, that you need to predict
germayne: for 2026, right? The data has something that's in the future, maybe you need to handle that. But I've done it in a way where your test data actually has a mix of, the different timestamps, right? So doing this doesn't matter.
germayne: But, not saying that you shouldn't do this in production.
germayne: Okay?
germayne: So within the notebook, you will see that the library has it, but honestly speaking, even without the library, you can easily do this split lah, right? You're just cutting by the timestamp. Less than a timestamp, more than a timestamp, correct?
germayne: Okay, so the next thing, right, we want to talk about is also the metric, right?
germayne: What are some of the metrics that you guys remember?
germayne: From regression.
germayne: What are some metrics that you guys remember?
germayne: One metric out of a hit. What was it?
Teng Lee LIM: main square area.
germayne: mean square arrow, root mean square arrow, right, mean absolute error. So, actually, today we're going to introduce another one, it's called mean absolute percentage error, right? It's called…
germayne: MAPE. So what it basically means is that it's just going to be expressed in terms of a percentage.
germayne: Right? Right. What is the average absolute percentage error that you're making?
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Right. So why can't we use the old, old ones?
germayne: You can, you can, you can. You can, you can. You can still use the old ones, but this is just…
germayne: from the time series methodology, they also use, make…
germayne: And, again, right, again, right, just to say, just to emphasize, these metrics are not exclusive to time series. They are just exclusive
germayne: they're not exclusive, they're only exclusive to regression problems, okay? But we're just introducing them. It's time to introduce, okay? But you can use them in other regression problems, and very common in research papers that you see that mean absolute error is published.
germayne: somebody wants to make a guess, why do you think mean absolute percentage error is popular? Anybody wants to make a guess. It's actually quite popular. Popular, but why? Why do you think mean absolute percentage error is popular?
Low Keng Teck, Noel: I don't think my percentage is very intuitive. Exactly.
germayne: Exactly. Business people, they hear percentage, they like it, right? Because everybody can understand percentage.
germayne: Right? How far is the prediction? Right? But the problem with mean absolute percentage error, there's a very huge drawback, okay? And you guys can test this out empirically, but the math is actually very simple, because you're calculating percentage.
germayne: If you are always under-predicting.
germayne: the ceiling to under-predict is 0%. So let's say if you're always constantly underestimating, right? Your house is $1 million, the actual target labor, you predict
germayne: 50K, right?
germayne: The… the… the ceiling of mistake that you can make around is at most 100%, sorry, 100% error.
germayne: Not 0%, right? 100% error.
germayne: However, if you over-predict, your mistake can go beyond 100%.
germayne: So basically, what it's telling you is that the penalty for under-prediction is heavier than over-prediction.
germayne: So if, let's say, you have a model that constantly under-predicts, the MAPE might be better.
germayne: And that is the drawback.
germayne: Okay?
germayne: So, of course, then, because of the drawback, you can do weighted MAP.
germayne: So basically, what this is trying to do is you weigh the instance, right? You want to give some kind of weight. For each of your instance, if it's a high prediction, you can weigh it higher.
germayne: So this is also another variant of MAPE, but however, you want to weigh the MAPE here, right? The idea here is that maybe for some of the predictions that you underestimate, maybe if they are not important, it might not take up a huge weight.
germayne: Okay, so this is weighted MEP. So for each instance, each data point, you weigh them differently, based on the actual prediction.
germayne: Right, you can see here, WI is basically the weight of the actual prediction. So maybe in this interpretation, if you're using weighted MAPE, you're just basically trying to say, I'm giving higher weight for higher actual value. If I'm predicting a flat for $5 million.
germayne: I make sure I get a $5 million flat right, as compared to a house that is $100,000.
germayne: Okay?
germayne: Now, of course, there's also another variant, symmetric MAPE. This is obviously used to solve the problem of MAPE, where it's not symmetrical, right? What it means, again, is
germayne: Previously, MAPE, been analyzed.
germayne: under-prediction, less than over-prediction, right? If you over-predict, well, you can… you can go above 100% error, but if you underestimate at most 100%, right? So what symmetric does is that it basically makes them symmetrical.
germayne: Okay, so there's a few variants.
germayne: And of course, again, this has nothing to do with time series in particular. I think methodology-wise, time series does use this, but you can also use this for your regression metrics.
germayne: Okay, so, soon we'll go through the notebook later on for this, but essentially it's the same metric, the drawback is the same, nothing changes, right? Which is why time series is not a… there's no difference in time series in particular, it's just that it's a different domain, right? But you're still doing regression.
germayne: Okay, so I think right now, you guys have access to most of the, evaluation metrics. Of course, now you guys will be the most familiar with RMSE, because in the Kaggle competition, it's done in RMSE, right?
germayne: Okay, so I think… I think we will… we will move on to the notebook, then when we come back, we will do the final… final portion, which is the forecasting model.
germayne: Alright.
germayne: Any questions so far, for me, with regards to the metric and validation?
germayne: Straightforward, right? Conceptually.
germayne: Okay?
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Miller.
germayne: Richard, formula.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: I mean, similar to what we've learned.
germayne: Yeah, yeah. So just… just introducing a different way to measure the… the arrow.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: That points back to the… remember that time you talked about the metrics, right?
Low Keng Teck, Noel: You know that metrics, we need to know the metrics before we start doing the model and that kind of stuff.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: So in this case…
Low Keng Teck, Noel: I agree with you, lah, because, like, going through all the effort, then realized, lah, you know what? So, it's actually good to know the metrics, but… So, in that case, what sort of…
Low Keng Teck, Noel: I mean, like, I know you say it's related to some business and everything, but… But then…
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Let's say you don't know anything, you go in there cold and everything, then how do you know, how do you start to…
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Know which metric it says, you should take.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: I mean, like, maybe I think the popular one?
Low Keng Teck, Noel: That will do.
germayne: Very, very good question, very good question. So, in reality, right… okay, I think maybe one thing to address lah. So, the difficult reality is you do need to know what you want, right? That's a difficult reality. You cannot go in cold. So, you need to spend the time to understand the trade-off.
germayne: Right? Of course, in reality, business people are not technical people. It's just reality, right?
germayne: But as the technical team, you need to be able to know the metric, because otherwise, you know, not everybody's just blind. The blind.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: And I also need to explain to them, right?
germayne: Right, exactly, exactly, exactly, exactly.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Okay, I don't know how this video.
germayne: So you guys realize it's actually a very hard skill set, and… and I know I'm digressing a bit to talk a bit, right, but this is a good, this is a very good question. You know I always tell people, okay, again, I'm not sure whether this is a fair statement, this is my opinion, and might be anecdotal experience, right? Because I only have one sample size.
germayne: But the reality is that in the technical track.
germayne: If you are the data science team and versus the engineering team.
germayne: If you… if you want to do well as a data science team, you need to know how to talk.
germayne: The reason for that is because you're always sitting in the intersection between business. You're not an engineer. And not… that's not to say that engineering cannot… oh, it's okay to get away with engineering. Engineering, right, if you cannot talk, you cannot explain, maybe it's okay.
germayne: Right? But from a data perspective, even if you are not very senior, of course, the more senior you are, the more you need to know how to explain, right? For example, I don't talk to… when I talk to people, I talk to the C-level. And if you can imagine.
germayne: business people, they don't want to know the math. It's like, you don't go and, you know, you don't… you don't write the equation for them, they don't care, right? So you need to know how to explain, you need to know how to… and in order to explain, sometimes you need to know your stuff, you need to know what's the trade-off.
germayne: But my point is that for data science or data, right, in general.
germayne: I feel that you need to know how to communicate, because you're always talking to product, you're always talking to business people. And business people…
germayne: usually they have certain understanding, and it's your job to guide them. So, for example, in this example, right, you know that MEPE is not exactly the right thing. So sometimes they might be like, oh, can we just do percentage error? Maybe percentage error might be easy to interpret, right?
germayne: Fair, right?
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Fair. No, exactly.
germayne: It's a very fair ask, right? Because to them, to them, they might be like, okay, I might want to know percentage error because
germayne: maybe sometimes when you miss… when you… let's say if you use MAPE, if you mispredict, I do not know whether you're doing it correctly for the larger value, let's say for the higher value, the $5 million flats.
germayne: Maybe I'm interested that… I know, you can go wrong on the less value flat, maybe for the high value flats, you need to make sure your prediction is correct, but how do I know if you're just giving me RMSE? You give me a number, 21,000, how do I know whether you're making $21,000 mistake? Is it, like, a general thing, or is it, like, I don't know.
germayne: So then it becomes very hard to interpret, right? So maybe they were like, okay, can I have percentage error? I want to know, in general, what's your percentage.
germayne: And then it's up to you to then decide, like, okay, what's the trade-off of using percentage? There's no right or wrong answer, in reality. You need to know why, and if this will enable you to make the right decision.
germayne: Okay?
germayne: Okay, anyway, Zach, we can talk more on Saturday, I think, now that we are towards the end, but I think these are all very important things, but Zach, yeah, Zach.
Zac Ang: I mean…
Zac Ang: just so, I think, in line with the interpretation part, I'm just wondering if we will also learn how to
Zac Ang: Identify the causes.
Zac Ang: So, for example, we are going to talk about how to do the prediction, but, like, what are the factors that is causing this? Like, how do we narrow down to say that this is the reason, that is the reason, for example?
germayne: How… for the arrow, is it?
Zac Ang: Meaning, like, so if we are predicting, say, if we are doing a time series for housing prices, then how do we then narrow it down and say that this is the reason for…
Zac Ang: the increase, or this variable leads to X percentage of this increase, something like that.
germayne: Also, you're talking about interpretation, is it?
Zac Ang: I mean, a copy of that.
germayne: Okay, I think, right, interpretation, I don't think we have it in the course, but I think maybe for a Saturday, I can introduce you guys another book. I'd like to introduce you guys' book, right? So, I'll introduce some common methodology for interpretation.
germayne: Interpretation has… okay, so I think to answer Zach's question, right, it's more of diagnosis, right? Let's say if you have a model, you might want to diagnose further to understand what are some of the things that is not doing well, and am I able to interpret what the model is doing, right?
germayne: if you are doing linear regression model that we have thought, very easy to interpret, correct? But what if you are… what if, let's say, you are not using linear regression, you are using some complex model?
germayne: there are some methodologies externally to do, right? It's called interpretation, right? And there's a very, very good book for it. So, maybe on a Saturday that we are free, towards the end, we can talk a bit about that.
germayne: Okay, about interpretation. But I can tell you, right, long story short, no matter the tools, right, if you have a very complex algorithm, business will not accept it, even though you can diagnose it. That's the… that's the fact.
germayne: Yeah, unfortunately, lah, right? If, let's say, you want to make some kind of business decision, then people are like, okay, why is it saying the house is like that? Why?
germayne: And you can have a lot of diagnostics too, but
germayne: sometimes it's just very hard to sell that, unfortunately, lah. Unfortunately, I think, from what I have seen, I've seen from both, even from a tech company perspective, if there are, like, some very crazy business decision, right, and then you have a very complex model, and now all the models that we are learning are getting more complex, which means that their interpretation is not, it's a black box.
germayne: So you can use other mechanisms, which I can introduce probably on Saturday, and of course, I'll give you guys the book, right? You guys, we won't teach it, but can tell you guys what people use.
germayne: But the ultimate fact is that even if you can diagnose, right, ultimately it will still be, will still be within the tech team.
germayne: usually business people have a tendency to not accept, which is why now you guys understand why I mention in a lot of places
germayne: People still use linear regression because it's easy to interpret, easy to understand. You guys understand, right? Yeah.
germayne: Yeah. Unless you are telling me that you are just pure prediction, the company doesn't need to make an action, there's no incentive to make some kind of decision-making, then people might not care about the interpretation.
germayne: But, of course, like what Zach is saying, maybe you want to do some diagnostic. I want to know, let's say I put in 100 variables, which variable is actually
germayne: influencing the outcome. You… there are methods for that, and that is… and it's a very well-researched area for interpret… Interpretation of black box models. Okay, but I… I think taken, note taken, we can see whether Saturday… not this Saturday lah, right? Maybe towards the end, we'll see whether I have a slot… I'll give a slot for interpreting models.
germayne: Okay, but you guys can start to see, yeah, these trade-offs.
germayne: Okay, I think that's all. Good questions so far, point taken. So, I think let's continue on notebook, otherwise we won't have time for… for the last part. Okay, soon, you ready?
Soon | NTU: Okay.
germayne: I think soon you have, like, the toxic fumes in your place, is it?
Soon | NTU: Don't know whether I can sleep tonight, huh?
Soon | NTU: Yeah, okay, let me share the screen.
Soon | NTU: Right? So we are in this, part 3 of the lesson, the notebook lesson.
Soon | NTU: Now, we are now in the topic on the time series forecasting and model evaluation. Okay, so before we go into evaluation or using the respective, metrics that we have seen, okay, so we will not go to each and every
Soon | NTU: metrics to evaluate the model, but we only focus on, this symmetric, Mean absolute percentage error.
Soon | NTU: Okay, for this, lesson, okay? So, just now, we have seen, right, Jamin has already shared with you, why the importance of retaining this, temporal sequence in your dataset, right, so that whatever you have in your training dataset, there must not be
Soon | NTU: Like, randomly mixed up with your… Test dataset.
Soon | NTU: future and the historical data, you know, all messed up. So that is why we cannot, make use of the
Soon | NTU: sklearn train-test split function, and instead, we need to make use of this very special temporal train-test split. Okay, by the way, we're at this, time series forecasting
Soon | NTU: Outline section, right? Right.
Soon | NTU: So… Now, if we were to go through… so we have all these… different… Performance metrics?
Soon | NTU: Right?
Soon | NTU: Okay, so we're going to use only this for the illustration, right?
Soon | NTU: And then? No.
Soon | NTU: Before we go into the…
Soon | NTU: the forecasting techniques, right? So, let's take a few steps back to
Soon | NTU: look at what are some of the, forecasting techniques, right, which, we can, use before we even go into, seriously looking at using Arima.
Soon | NTU: the modeling technique to further, you know, do your time series data analysis, okay? Now, this, concept is called the naive forecasting.
Soon | NTU: Okay.
Soon | NTU: why is it called naive, right? Because we just assume the simplest form of prediction, right? We don't want to take into account the trend, seasonality, and other patterns in the data, right? For example.
Soon | NTU: cycle.
Soon | NTU: Okay? Cyclic, so-called variations, okay? So…
Soon | NTU: let's take the naive approach, right? Don't, don't think too complicated, right? So, the way I would like it, right? Okay? So, what are some of the options available? Okay, so now, if, you can refer to this book, right.
Soon | NTU: Right.
Soon | NTU: Recommended by, Jermaine, right? So I have this link here.
Soon | NTU: Okay, let me share with you.
Soon | NTU: Jermine also have, shared with you the link, but I…
Soon | NTU: I'll give you the link here as well. Okay, let me…
Soon | NTU: Okay, so this is in, Chapter 3. So this particular page, right.
Soon | NTU: So basically, it's telling you, oh, if you want to use this different option of the naive forecasting method, okay, so this is what you'll get.
Soon | NTU: Sorry? Biscuit, yeah, 3.
Soon | NTU: Mean?
Soon | NTU: Based on the last value, and also the seasonal naive.
Soon | NTU: Right?
Soon | NTU: So, very, very simple, or you don't care whether there's a seasonality, okay, we don't care whether there's a trend, where there are, other kind of a pattern or component in your data. We just want to make it simple, okay? And very often, we use this as,
Soon | NTU: a baseline model, okay, to compare it against your ARIMA model, which we are going to do in the subsequent section, right?
Soon | NTU: Are you able to improve the metrics by maybe a significant amount, right, using the ARIMA compared to the naive forecasting technique?
Soon | NTU: Right? If not, then… why do Arima in the first place, right? Okay, so this is, very good.
Soon | NTU: starting point?
Soon | NTU: to form your baseline model for your time series analysis, okay? So, let's go through the codes, right? So, we will import the
Soon | NTU: naive forecaster.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so let's take the naive approach first to go through and see how we can actually make use of this to forecast the value.
Soon | NTU: And you notice here, so this is what we have already seen.
Soon | NTU: plot series.
Soon | NTU: Right, just now.
Soon | NTU: And now, this is the important…
Soon | NTU: One, we are going to use a train-test split, but a very special temporal train-test split to split your training data, your time series data in two.
Soon | NTU: Cream and test.
Soon | NTU: dataset, right?
Soon | NTU: So, in a case What is our wine, right?
Soon | NTU: The reason why we
Soon | NTU: loaded the airline passenger data set, again, is because we just want to, you know, adopt the same kind of consistent variable naming convention, right? As you know, our data
Soon | NTU: Usually, we use a capital X to label, you know, our feature, and then our
Soon | NTU: label column are the small y, right? But in this case, we do not have any feature
Soon | NTU: Our feature are… the white itself, but…
Soon | NTU: in the historical one, comparing itself in the current time. So…
Soon | NTU: our feature is actually only Y, comparing it by… with itself. Okay, so we only have Y here.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so now this temporal train test split will give us a train
Soon | NTU: and test data. Okay, so since we specified the test size as 36,
Soon | NTU: Now, remember, our why is money data, right?
Soon | NTU: Monthly data in how many data points?
Soon | NTU: How many data points do we have?
Phillip Tan Lip Teck: Golf bite. Golf.
Soon | NTU: 12 by 12 is 1 for 4, right? Okay, so if we have 36 months… now, this is, in terms of
Soon | NTU: 36 months, so we will have the remaining 108 months in our training data.
Soon | NTU: Okay.
Soon | NTU: So, we just take a look at what we have here, okay? So, the first month in our test set is starting from the 1958 January
Soon | NTU: 300 over.
Soon | NTU: 340 is the first value, and then the shape is 108 in our training data set, right? So it's quite aligned to our,
Soon | NTU: so-called the, mathematics, right? 36 plus 104 equals to 144.
Soon | NTU: monthly data point.
Soon | NTU: Okay.
Soon | NTU: No.
Soon | NTU: No, we… Create a naive forecaster variable.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so we call this function. So what we have is, we are now making use of this first method.
Soon | NTU: Naive.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so this is here.
Soon | NTU: So, your black line, right, so assuming this is our…
Soon | NTU: airline passenger data set. Okay, so the last point is over here.
Soon | NTU: Right? So the last is… We will predict, based on the last value.
Soon | NTU: And then continually just throw one, like, As simple as that.
Soon | NTU: Okay? Nothing very complicated, right? Right? That is why it's called naive.
Soon | NTU: Wing.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so we train our… Forecasting, model.
Soon | NTU: Okay, with our training data, And then, we are going to… Specify our forecasting horizon.
Soon | NTU: FH.
Soon | NTU: Right? So this means, because when, in Python, we usually ignore the last value when you say.
Soon | NTU: array branch. Okay, so that's why we need to… Add one more.
Soon | NTU: Value back to the second value, so that we have a total of 60 point.
Soon | NTU: Okay? To draw it from here to here.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so now we are going to use our naive forecasting model to create it, right?
Soon | NTU: FH is… how many… Okay, so it's about 36 data points.
Soon | NTU: Because this is 1 to 37, right? So we're gonna have 1, 2, 36, and this is what we have here. You just simply throw a line.
Soon | NTU: from here… Until all the way to the last December of, 1960.
Soon | NTU: Okay.
Soon | NTU: So, very, very simple, right, to do your forecasting.
Soon | NTU: Using a naive, forecasting technique.
Soon | NTU: And what is the value of this?
Soon | NTU: What's the value here?
Soon | NTU: Anyone want to guess?
Soon | NTU: I'll give you 30 seconds.
Chieh Cheng Lai: Rich?
Chieh Cheng Lai: Average.
Soon | NTU: What is the value?
Low Keng Teck, Noel: We call you?
Soon | NTU: Because I say last, right?
Soon | NTU: So, last… So that's why we draw a horizontal line, but if you…
Soon | NTU: extend this line to the vertical axis, right? Okay, so there must be a value, right?
Soon | NTU: That the system have chosen to draw this line.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Based on the data is 340.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: I think.
Soon | NTU: This is an ally, dataset.
Soon | NTU: Can someone tell me?
Chieh Cheng Lai: Starting… starting value.
Chieh Cheng Lai: Sure, interesting.
Soon | NTU: Pre-hano over, you can tell, right?
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Yeah, about 340.
Soon | NTU: Why 340?
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Because, january 1958, it's 340.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Based on the data, the previous cell, there's a…
Soon | NTU: Miracles and vegetables.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Euro.
Soon | NTU: Okay, let me… Okay.
Soon | NTU: Okay.
Soon | NTU: Peggy.
Soon | NTU: So, your 340 is the blue dot.
Soon | NTU: Okay, 340 is the blue dot, right? Okay, so 30 seconds over. Now, 340 is the data point
Soon | NTU: on the 1958 January, okay? Now, last is the last data point of the training data set.
Soon | NTU: Which is 1957 December.
Soon | NTU: Okay? That is why… It is not 340, which is this blue dot, but it's some value lower
Soon | NTU: LAN 340.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so if you can use, the tail function, okay, so you can just work it out, right? Call the tail function on the Y train.
Soon | NTU: Okay, let me try now,
Soon | NTU: Okay, so it's, the last ticker point is 336. So this line is 336.
Soon | NTU: If you, extrapolate, Okay, so 336 is the number very close to 340.
Soon | NTU: 340 is a different data point. It's the data point in 1958 January, but this is the last data point of training data set, okay?
Soon | NTU: So, very good, try, well.
Soon | NTU: Okay, let me continue.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so with this, we call it the last…
Soon | NTU: the strategy, right? We have about 4 different strategies for this naive forecaster, okay, but we have seen this last value is one of the most simplest form of a naive forecasting technique, right? Simply take the last value of your training data, and then you just
Soon | NTU: Draw a horizontal line, okay?
Soon | NTU: No.
Soon | NTU: This… code block, right, basically is making use of this, and then trying to give you this
Soon | NTU: a forecasting technique called the rolling origin. Okay, so basically, instead of using just one data point.
Soon | NTU: as the basis for your prediction, okay? So, this…
Soon | NTU: Code block is basically going to predict only One data point a hit.
Soon | NTU: based on the last value you have accumulated so far in the predict values, predicted value, okay? So, if you go through this code, right.
Soon | NTU: So basically, what you get is… You have,
Soon | NTU: A predicted value, okay, a prediction
Soon | NTU: Just similar to what you have in your test data, But it's…
Soon | NTU: With, a lack of one.
Soon | NTU: That means there is a one-month lag between your forecasted value in green.
Soon | NTU: The rolling origin prediction versus your… test data.
Soon | NTU: Okay, this is just an illustration to show, oh, you know, apart from drawing a one straight line like this.
Soon | NTU: You know, which may or may not have any side, because if your original time series have seasonal or trend, okay, so this kind of prediction is actually not very…
Soon | NTU: Not very useful and realistic, lah.
Soon | NTU: Right.
Soon | NTU: Okay, unless your original time series data is… has no train, Right.
Soon | NTU: Maybe as no season as well.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so this is an example of using The last value strategy.
Soon | NTU: Okay, for the naive forecasting technique.
Soon | NTU: to… Basically, to do prediction one step at a time, okay?
Soon | NTU: And this is what you get, okay? And now, let's take a look at the mean absolute percentage error.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so since this is a symmetric little true, right? So this is a symmetric mean absolute percentage error.
Soon | NTU: I think it's the last one which, Jimin shared with you in that last slide, sorry, okay? You can see…
Soon | NTU: The metrics is only 0.09.
Soon | NTU: Much lower than what we have in the…
Soon | NTU: last naive forecasting technique. This one is about…
Soon | NTU: This one is about 0.23 tomorrow.
Soon | NTU: Okay, you, you can, you can try it out, right?
Soon | NTU: How to get the, metrics Okay.
Soon | NTU: From your naive forecasting, based on the last value. Based on the rolling origin, Okay, so this is,
Soon | NTU: Basically, it's just very close to the… test data.
Soon | NTU: So you can see the… Matrix is quite low, 0.09.
Soon | NTU: Me.
Soon | NTU: No.
Soon | NTU: So far, any question?
Soon | NTU: If not, then we'll continue on to, another option, the strategic option, the strategy parameter. It's called a seasonal naive, okay? It's still naive, based on last value.
Soon | NTU: But take into account, instead of getting the value from the last data point of your training data.
Soon | NTU: Which, in the case of the… Loss.
Soon | NTU: Strategy equals.
Soon | NTU: The value is 336, right?
Soon | NTU: Okay.
Soon | NTU: Now, for naive lasts, right, without taking into account seasonal variations, okay, your value of your SP is
Soon | NTU: Default to 1.
Soon | NTU: This is equivalent to this.
Soon | NTU: Naive.
Soon | NTU: skiing.
Soon | NTU: This is… Last, but SP is 12.
Soon | NTU: I think this is called, seasonal parameter, if I'm not wrong, right? Okay, so with this.
Soon | NTU: We create another version of the forecast model based on the naive techniques.
Soon | NTU: And then… Likewise, we do a prediction based on this model, taking into account The seasonality, right?
Soon | NTU: But you can see… now you have a much lower last value. Okay, so this last value
Soon | NTU: is taken from the last seasonality of the 19… 57.
Soon | NTU: Okay, you can go and trace back how the chart of 1957, the first data point of the… when the season starts, okay? The season will look something like this.
Soon | NTU: Okay, it will repeat.
Soon | NTU: for the subsequent years. In fact, For all the years.
Soon | NTU: Right? Because seasonality, by definition, is,
Soon | NTU: Usually, we look at it some variation.
Soon | NTU: Up to 1 year period, okay?
Soon | NTU: So, as you can see.
Soon | NTU: this is not so, I would say, appropriate technique, okay, when there is some kind of a trend
Soon | NTU: hidden in your time series data, okay? So, as you can see.
Soon | NTU: Our forecast values are a bit… Underestimated, right?
Soon | NTU: More are very low.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so all this in orange, of the same… Magnitude, the Y value.
Soon | NTU: Pretty.
Soon | NTU: Now, ideos… train.
Soon | NTU: Your subsequent data point, the future data point, okay, would have Move up.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so we can see our actual data point Y, right?
Soon | NTU: Because of the trend, it has actually moved up. So, our forecasted value, using this naive forecasting method, even though we have taken seasonality into account.
Soon | NTU: It is still not.
Soon | NTU: As good as our rolling origin.
Soon | NTU: method, okay? But definitely, it is better than our naive.
Soon | NTU: forecasting techniques.
Soon | NTU: this is slightly better, okay? So, now… What is the mean absolute?
Soon | NTU: percentage error.
Soon | NTU: 0.14.
Soon | NTU: Okay, for our naive, forecasting technique based on the last value is about 0.23.
Soon | NTU: Right, if I'm not wrong.
Soon | NTU: Right? So this is the… how we actually make use of the naive forecasting technique to put prediction, okay?
Soon | NTU: And then, the next one is the drift… We don't have it here.
Soon | NTU: But I think, yeah.
Soon | NTU: There's an example of the… Naive forecasting.
Soon | NTU: Using the drift method.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so basically, You are.
Soon | NTU: Calculating
Soon | NTU: how much changes you have, okay, seen, you have observed in your data, okay, right from the very beginning of your
Soon | NTU: Training data, okay? The very first point.
Soon | NTU: 1949, right? January.
Soon | NTU: all the way until 1940, 9 December.
Soon | NTU: Okay? And then you… Go and calculate.
Soon | NTU: What is the slope from here Right.
Soon | NTU: tool here.
Soon | NTU: Okay.
Soon | NTU: So now, this slope, right?
Soon | NTU: We'll give you a number, And it will tell you how you're… Passenger count.
Soon | NTU: have increased Every month.
Soon | NTU: Right from 1949 all the way until 1957.
Soon | NTU: Right, because 1957 is our last year in our training dataset, right?
Soon | NTU: Okay.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so we get a slope aligned with some slope, rh, okay?
Soon | NTU: And then, based on our… formula here.
Soon | NTU: predict.
Soon | NTU: Same horizon, predict… forecasting horizon, 36 months.
Soon | NTU: Okay?
Soon | NTU: flood our… Data.
Soon | NTU: Test data versus a prediction.
Soon | NTU: And this is how your chart looks like. So this is a… tests.
Soon | NTU: Beta.
Soon | NTU: Okay? Your prediction is supposed to be as close to this as possible, but the drift method only takes into account the slope.
Soon | NTU: Okay, how much your passenger count changes over that
Soon | NTU: You know, that, that 9, 9, years, right?
Soon | NTU: And then this is… Y'all.
Soon | NTU: prediction.
Soon | NTU: Using the DRIG method.
Soon | NTU: Okay, is it?
Soon | NTU: Good compared to… the… Seasoned? Naive?
Soon | NTU: This is 0.14.
Soon | NTU: Just don't we have.
Soon | NTU: 0.1454.
Soon | NTU: Slightly better, right?
Soon | NTU: Okay, but I would say this kind of comparison is not conclusive.
Soon | NTU: Okay, sometimes you, will not see a pattern. Oh, the drift method is better, you know, because this drift
Soon | NTU: Due to the assistance of a trend inside your data, you know, probably you… your drift method will perform better than your seasonality.
Soon | NTU: Yay.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so this is how we…
Soon | NTU: Make our prediction using the various techniques, and then assess the performance of your Forecast value based on this
Soon | NTU: metrics.
Soon | NTU: Okay.
Soon | NTU: Now, this is false, right?
Soon | NTU: Your number will be just mean absolute percentage error.
Soon | NTU: If this is symmetric, Then you will take into account,
Soon | NTU: You know, the need to adjust for in case your, denominator is a zero.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so we have to… Account for that.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so this is, the third part of the, jupyter Notebook, session.
Soon | NTU: why it's so special? There's a question from
Soon | NTU: Xieqing, what is so special on this start value in the time series?
Soon | NTU: That is how the formula works, okay, especially for the drift method.
Soon | NTU: King.
Chieh Cheng Lai: Oh, so this is only applicable for this formula… I mean, this car formula? Yes, yes.
Soon | NTU: Correct.
Soon | NTU: Okay, for the drift method, okay, so as you can see.
Soon | NTU: If you were to recalculate the slope, right, from here to here, your slope is slightly… likely to be like this.
Soon | NTU: So, your drift matter basically is an extrapolation of the last point of your training data into the… Future.
Soon | NTU: forecasting horizon, which is 36 months, so it'll be like this.
Soon | NTU: Okay? This is a loss, this is a naive, And then your meaner.
Soon | NTU: is basically the mean of your data set. Okay, so you'll be somewhere here.
Soon | NTU: We don't have a code for the meaner, but you can actually try it out, right?
Soon | NTU: Okay, so I created a meme, and then forecast… And then, let's see… How is the…
Soon | NTU: metrics value look like. Okay, so mean is the worst performing model, 0.58.
Soon | NTU: Out of so many models.
Soon | NTU: Because… I don't think a meme.
Soon | NTU: It's a very good predictor, in this case, for the pathogen dataset.
Chieh Cheng Lai: Understand right now. Thank you.
Soon | NTU: Yeah, okay. Welcome.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so if you have any questions, you can continue to post in the chat or in the Discord later, right?
Soon | NTU: So I will… Okay, let me see. Okay, so Arima is the…
Soon | NTU: Last part of our lesson, so we'll go through that after the Do you mean section?
Soon | NTU: Jimmy?
Soon | NTU: Over to you.
germayne: Okay, thank, thank you, thank you, Sun.
germayne: Okay, you guys, okay, we continue?
germayne: But, I cannot see everybody's face.
germayne: Yeah, okay? You guys okay? Hit continue?
germayne: Okay, we finish up? We finish up? All good?
germayne: Okay.
germayne: Okay, so now we are at the last part, right? I think thanks, thanks soon for going through all the notebooks to build all the foundations. So, essentially, we are just really building the foundation, and today we are only going through to go through one forecasting
germayne: algorithm. I think it's a very, very traditional time series algorithm.
germayne: Okay, so essentially, it's really called the RMA model, and what we are going to go through, Arima, would be some of the assumptions that's required for the RMA model specifically, as well as
germayne: the different pieces of the Ariba model, right? So we have this auto-regression and the moving average model. Just to take note, right, this moving average is different from the moving average
germayne: aggregation that I talked about just now, okay? Just take note, huh? This is the moving average component of the Arima model. The previous one is the moving average aggregation, right? Where we slide the window to smoothen, so just be… just take note, it's a bit different.
germayne: Okay, so this is just really one algorithm. The notebook also has others, so we'll just talk about it, later, okay?
germayne: Okay, so one of the things before we talk a bit deeper about the RMR model is actually the first thing we need to talk about is this concept as stationarity. Okay, essentially, stationarity is critical for RMR model, as well as if you want to fit a linear regression model on a time series model, you need to remove away this
germayne: you need to ensure that there's a constant mean and constant variance across time. And the idea here is that if the time series actually still has seasonality and trend, it becomes very hard to model, okay? That is the assumptions behind Arima.
germayne: You will also have this intuition, right, if you think about it, right? If you think about…
germayne: three base models that we learned last week, right? If you guys remember, 3 base model.
germayne: Tree-based model obviously has a problem with extrapolating as well. If a tree model has not seen any value
germayne: From the dataset, it will not ever be able to predict a value that is outside of the dataset.
germayne: Right, if you think about it, if you remember, the tree model is always trying to split the data set into different leafs, into different leaf nodes, right? So if, let's say, your data set, right, in the resil data that you guys have, the resil data
germayne: If the data has never seen a residual house going above
germayne: 2 to 3 million, your tree base model will never be able to do that. So the idea here is actually also very similar. So what we want to do for Arima is, you somehow want to remove away this trend.
germayne: and the seasonality, so that the change is having this constant mean and constant variance, so that you can actually model it in the model, right? And then once the model has modeled that, then you can reverse transformation to
germayne: revert back the trend and the seasonality. So the idea here is that you want to remove them, so one of the big key assumptions behind our RIMA model is it needs to be stationary. Of course, you will see other algorithms like exponential smoothing, we will just talk about it. It doesn't really require stationarity as the prerequisite.
germayne: So the idea here, as you can see, right, the original data set here, a very famous dataset that's also used very repeatedly in the textbook, is the airline passengers dataset across time.
germayne: So, essentially, you can see that the number of people flying, taking flights in the airline actually increases since the 1950s, right? And one very obvious thing you can see here is what?
germayne: this is obviously a time series that has this multiplication pattern, right? You can see that the variance is actually increasing. So, it's clear that there is no constant mean, and there's no constant variation, because the variation is increasing. So, what you want to do here is that, actually, if you do a box cox.
germayne: transformation, and of course, a log transformation is just one, you know, the general form is actually the box force transformation. So actually, you notice that by doing a log transformation on this dataset, we actually reduce the variance, but the mean is not the same. The mean is actually increasing over time.
germayne: So what you want to do here is that the data, obviously, is not stationary, and what you want to do is you want to apply some kind of differencing, and by doing a differencing, you actually ensure that now they have constant mean and constant variance. You can see the variance is constant now, and if you look at the mean across the time series, it's actually constant.
germayne: So once the data is stationary, we can then apply RMA model in order to model this prediction, right? In order to model this specific dataset.
germayne: Okay, so one takeaway here later on is that I will introduce some kind of mechanism to test for stationarity, okay? You can apply some kind of statistical test, and at the same time.
germayne: take note, because the… the mechanism here is that differencing will remove the… the… will ensure that it's now stationary, the data, right? So…
germayne: If, let's say, your data set is, like, in percentage change, naturally, if you think about it from the formulation, right, if you calculate a percentage change over time.
germayne: Do you guys think that, naturally, it has some kind of differencing?
germayne: If it's a percentage.
germayne: if I'm calculating percentage change in GDP over time.
germayne: Do you guys think, like, there's a different scene done?
germayne: What do you guys think?
germayne: How do you calculate a percentage change?
germayne: How do you guys calculate a percentage change? What's the formula for percentage change?
germayne: You take the difference with the previous value, right?
germayne: Then you multiply by 100, right? You take the denominator as the previous value, and so the idea here is that, naturally, there are some metric that is… that will naturally be stationary.
germayne: Okay?
germayne: Okay, so the first important takeaway is for RMR model, you need to ensure that the data is stationary, which means that the takeaway here is constant mean, constant variance, okay? And the first form of the RMR model is actually what we call the autoregressive model, okay?
germayne: you may not want, you know, you might not be using this autoregressive model, but there's actually a very strong takeaway from this model, which I'll talk about it at the end, towards machine learning models, okay? But for the RMA concept.
germayne: the first… the first very simple model that Arima has is actually the AR model, so it's essentially what we call an autoregressive model. When people say autoregressive, essentially you're trying to model, right, if you look at the equation, I'm trying to model
germayne: the timestamp YT, I'm actually trying to model against the lag values. So you can see YT-1, plus YT minus 2, etc, all the way to YT minus P.
germayne: So this defines the order of the AR model, and how many autoregressive terms I want to regress against, right?
germayne: And you can see this is also a linear model, right? But the AR model, essentially, what we are just trying to say is that, you know, a certain prediction is actually based on the previous prediction.
germayne: And actually, this makes a lot of sense in reality, right? If you think about the data as a sequential data, modeling the autoregressive signals actually captures very strong signal to make a prediction, right? If you think about it, right, if you think about, like, a traffic condition, before there's a peak.
germayne: Right? If, let's say, there's a peak at 6.30, 6 to 6.30pm, where everybody is leaving the office.
germayne: if I were to know that the next… the previous two time period actually has a pick, then from the dataset, I should be able to know that after the pick, there might be a drop, right? After there's a traffic peak, correct? Same thing as your 6… from 6PM
germayne: sorry, 6am all the way to 9pm, right, where, you know, you might expect an increase in traffic, right? And after that, there might be a drop. So essentially, when you model something using autoregressive terms, you can actually capture very, very strong signal, especially for sequential data. So that's the first takeaway.
germayne: And of course, right, if you think about Arima, the second component is called the moving average.
germayne: The idea here is that, from autoregressive perspective, you want to model the previous lak terms in order to predict the future term, right? So what the moving average is modeling is that instead you're modeling the previous
germayne: residual, right? The intuition here is that you are trying to say that previous surprises, because errors are due to things that you cannot predict, right? These are all the residual errors. What it's trying to model is that if I were to look at certain surprises in the past, I should be able to get a sense of the prediction in the future.
germayne: So what the moving average model here is, that you are actually moving with some kind of order, right, a Q number of historical residuals, right? Because
germayne: Using the… using the training data that you have, you have access to n number of… P number of timestamps, right? What you can do is you essentially can calculate the residual prediction.
germayne: Right? And you can essentially model against the historical error. So basically, what we are trying to see here is that the equation from an MA perspective is we are modeling against the historical residual up to Q term.
germayne: Right, look at the term here, Q. And if you look at the autoregressive term here is P. So you will see later that we have to define P and Q in order to determine this linear model, which will allow us to make the prediction.
germayne: Okay?
germayne: So, of course, the idea here is you combine them into Arima, okay?
germayne: anybody wants to make a guess what the… where is the I? So AR comes from the fact that we are going to model the autoregressive terms, right? That's an AR. MA, actually, the… we want to model the historical errors. Where do you think the I is?
germayne: Anybody knows?
germayne: No. So, essentially, the I, right, is that what… how many differencing that we need to make? So, essentially, the parameter D, right? So essentially here, if you were to look into a lot of, like, the libraries, essentially, it allows you to define how many differencing that you need to make. And why do we need to make the differencing? It's because we need to make sure that the series is stationary.
germayne: Okay? So what this means is that, in terms of parameter, the P
germayne: The D and the Q is basically now the knob that you need to adjust in order to define the RMR model.
germayne: Right? So the P determines how many autoregressive terms we want, how many lags we want to think about. The Q is how many historical residual do we want to model, and the D, essentially, is the differencing.
germayne: the number of differencing that is needed to make the series stationary, okay? Of course, Professor Robb in the textbook says that most of the time.
germayne: two differences are max. Typically, you don't go beyond two differencing, right, empirically.
germayne: Okay?
germayne: So, of course, if you put the whole formula together, you have this whole formula that's, again, defined by the intercept C plus
germayne: the parameter of YT-1 all the way to YT minus B.
germayne: Right? So the P parameter defines how many regressive terms that you will define. So there's P terms here, there's one term here, and then here you have Q number of terms. So in total, the number of parameters is 1 plus P plus Q. That is the total definition of your REMA model.
germayne: Okay?
germayne: So here, basically, you can see that this is the… the… the parameters. Here, right, I'll talk a bit about the KPSS test, but essentially, the idea here is that
germayne: you can either use the ACF and PACF diagram to actually do some diagnostic to understand if the series is stationary, or even better, you just do the KPSS test, okay? There are a lot of stationary tests. You might go online, you might see that, oh, there's unit route tests, there's stationary t-test. I think KPSS is a unit root test. So, essentially, it is recommended, okay, at least empirically, it has been
germayne: tested.
germayne: by Professor Rob, he said that in his own blog, that KPSS test empirically does better, okay? So what KPSS tests, later we'll talk about it, is that it's a statistical test.
germayne: You essentially can apply this test to determine if the differencing is enough to make the data stationary. So you just need to do a statistical test. And that's where knowing how to use the p-value to reject
germayne: The null hypothesis will come into play, because you need to apply the test to determine
germayne: if the data is stationary or not, okay? So you can see here it's KPSS test. We'll talk about it later.
germayne: Of course, there's a P and Q here.
germayne: For the next, 10 minutes, we need to talk about how to determine the P&Q, okay? And I'll tell you guys what the industry practice is to actually to determine the P and Q.
germayne: Okay, so a very big part, if you go into many literature, just to take note, right, Arima is not, like, the first time people is teaching here, right? It's so traditional that this has been, like, old school. This is basically an old school method, right? So there are many literatures on it. And if you go online and check, right, they will actually ask you to use the ACF and
germayne: PACF,
germayne: graph in order to determine the order, right? Now, in practice, okay, what people usually do is, first, you use a KPSS test.
germayne: is super, super important test. I think just now, soon, he showed the, augmented DK Fuller test, ADF test. In general, I think if you just stick with KPSS test, that will be good enough, okay? Because in the library, usually, you can choose what test it is, but I would suggest KPSS test. I think if the exercise is doing ADF test, I think it's fine, but…
germayne: In practice, people usually do KPSS tests, alright, the recommended one.
germayne: And the KPSS test, if you can see, right, essentially, you're just doing a null hypothesis to test if the series is stationary. So all you need to do is to just check the p-value, right, to determine if it should reject or do not reject the null hypothesis.
germayne: Okay? So you can perform the unit root test first to determine the stationary or non-stationary. Then usually what people do is, instead of doing the ACF and PACF graph, right, because they will be like, oh, no, you look at the graph, if the value… so if you remember, the ACF and PACF graph looks something like that.
germayne: So people will tell you, like, oh, you know, you need to check the lag here, then determine the order. The good news, right, good news, right, lucky for you guys, a lot of these methods is because in the past, computation is hard.
germayne: So people need to do that using, all these methods to determine. But now computation is cheap, right? Especially on, Arima models, especially if you are doing, univariate… univariate, basically, you only got one variable, which is your Y variable, right? You only got one column.
germayne: I'm sure everyone's computer here can run these multiple times, so the good news is that you can actually calculate the order, you can do order selection. Order selection basically means choose the best P and choose the best Q. The good news is you can just choose this automatically.
germayne: Right? I'm sure you guys will be like, oh my god, I'm so thankful, right? Yeah, I'm so thankful because, essentially, I cut out, like, 5 slides in order to explain how to choose the order, right? You can just brute force this, you can compute this.
germayne: Now, I want to ask you guys a question.
germayne: If, hypothetically, I'm not teaching you guys how to do the P&Q, with whatever that you guys have been equipped with.
germayne: Hypothetically, if you can, you know, fit all the different P's and all the different queues, what will you… how will you guys do the calculation?
germayne: Can somebody try to give me an intuition? You guys have the tools already.
Phillip Tan Lip Teck: Even.
germayne: If, let's say, you don't have the slide here.
germayne: How will you choose the P and Q?
Phillip Tan Lip Teck: radiant, that's…
germayne: Huh?
Phillip Tan Lip Teck: do gradient testing.
germayne: Grade… what, what, sorry, what's gradient testing?
germayne: Is there some class you attend?
germayne: Which? Which one?
Zac Ang: I will do a while loop.
germayne: And what will you test? How will you know which is the best?
germayne: So, in your Kaggle, what have you guys been doing? How do you know what you're doing is correct?
Zac Ang: Test for the mean square error.
germayne: You do a… exactly, you do a cross-validation, right?
germayne: So, the idea here is actually very simple, right?
germayne: If you… even if you're not taught this, right, hypothetically, you can actually brute force the P and Q, because the permutation is actually not… not too bad, and you can fit this model very, very quickly, right? But the good news is that there's actually a method. We're going to talk a bit about it, right? We're going to talk a bit about this thing called AIC, BIC, and AICC.
germayne: So essentially, when you use… and good news, later on, I think we'll go through some of these, methods in the algorithm. Essentially, you can choose the best P and Q, empirically, using these three mechanisms. It's actually called the,
germayne: Why is it called R?
germayne: It's basically the information criterion that we can actually use to test empirically, right? And the… the…
germayne: The idea here is that because
germayne: how the model actually fits the P and Q is that it's actually doing something called the maximum likelihood estimation. And mathematically, maximizing the likelihood estimation is the same as minimizing mean square error.
germayne: Okay.
germayne: So basically, right, you can actually use this to sort of choose what is the best parameter, and some libraries do this for you automatically, okay? And we'll go through this called, this method called Auto Arima.
germayne: Where Professor Robheimer, I believe he's the one that created Auto Arima.
germayne: Okay.
germayne: So essentially, there's this thing called the information criterion. I'm just summarizing this, it's actually not super difficult. If you are interested in the math, you guys can just go and Wikipedia the math. But the idea here is that all of these three information criteria
germayne: they actually capture a portion of the negative log likelihood, right? So if you remember, right, the algorithm needs some kind of… if you guys remember, previously we talked about decision trees.
germayne: We talk a bit about linear regression. Under the hood, there's a kind of loss function that is actually been getting minimized. But here, right, essentially the parameters for P and Q is actually search.
germayne: using the maximum log likelihood, which is the same as minimizing mean square error, mathematically, okay? So, the idea here is that it's actually fitting to find the best P and Q, but we have 3 different criteria to evaluate.
germayne: this P and Q, right? How do you search for the best P and Q? So imagine, right, that Elgo will just basically do a loop and just basically fit different parameters. And I believe it might have some mechanism, later we'll see the pseudocode from Auto Arima, but the idea here is that it will search for P and Q in a smart manner, and it will find… and you get to choose whether you want to use
germayne: AIC, AICC, or BIC, okay?
germayne: And each of these three things actually look for different things, okay? So what the AIC, right, mathematically, is that it's actually looking at the negative log likelihood.
germayne: Basically, what this means is that you want the log likelihood to be the highest, so negative log likelihood will basically make it the smallest, right? So the highest basically means the smallest. So you're basically just taking the sum of the negative log likelihood with the number of parameters. And you guys might have this intuition that, hey, actually this is very similar to rich regression.
germayne: If you guys remember, right?
germayne: remember, last week, we talked about the rich and the lasso? So basically, the rich and lasso, they added the parameter along with the loss function, right? So essentially, you're saying that
germayne: I want some… I want my loss to be very small, but at the same time, I don't want my parameter to be, you know, too many parameters, because I'll overfit, right? So basically, what AIC does is that AIC adds the parameter in the AIC computation so that
germayne: When you want to choose the AIC to be very small, you don't want to just choose a model that has a lot of parameters, a lot of P and Q, because
germayne: If P and Q increases.
germayne: my entire, you know, Arima model becomes very complex, right? Because the parameters becomes bigger. I have, my YT minus 1 all the way to YT minus P, and then my epsilon t minus 1 all the way to epsilon t minus Q. So, you can think about it, right?
germayne: The more… the more parameters, obviously the model will be better. Better in a sense of, like, overfitting the dataset, right? Same thing as putting more features into your model for your Kaggle.
germayne: So the idea here is that AIC, alright, actually sort of penalizes the parameters, and if the data… if your sample set is actually very large, it's very similar to LOO, basically the look… the lift one out, cross-validation slash the walk-forward, the one that we have been doing.
germayne: So mathematically, right, AIC actually allows us to choose what is a good model, right?
germayne: But however, AICC also has problems. You can see here that AICC, you know, if your data set is very small, it might still choose a… it might still choose a model that is very complex. So people invented AICC, right, and they recommend AICC to be… to be the criterion to choose, if you were to do auto-arima.
germayne: Then there's also BIC, where it also penalizes the parameters even more, right?
germayne: Don't need to talk about the math, but the idea here is that
germayne: These three information criteria, you choose the smallest, the better.
germayne: And why is this important? Because Auto Arima allows you to define these three, and it will automatically select the best P and the best Q. Okay? For you.
germayne: Okay, so you can see this is the… again, this is listed in the textbook. The AutoRima algorithm obviously came from these two guys, so Hyman is basically Rob Hyman's surname.
germayne: And then I, Kandaka, I think, is another professor that does this. So two of them actually created this AutoRMR algorithm, they're the one that created it. So essentially, they will do KPSS tests automatically for you to determine the number of difference.
germayne: it will then minimize AICC, depending on what you choose, and it will choose the best P and Q, right? And it will just iterate and fit the model for you. And in practice, this function runs very, very fast.
germayne: Okay? So, good news for you guys. In general, I don't think anybody now still look at the PACF, ACF and PACF chart. If it's for prediction.
germayne: you can empirically test it, which is the beauty of doing prediction, right? Prediction is super easy. You can always validate this, right? If you're doing something like Kaggle, you always have some kind of ground truth to test.
germayne: Right.
germayne: Okay, so, I would say interpretation is not that, important, right? But the idea is that autoregressive, you start to notice that we are actually modeling historical values with your Y target variable, because we are trying to say that for sequential data.
germayne: Right? Modeling the historical value will tell me the relationship, right? I'm always modeling the historical lag values, right? I'm saying that the previous steps allow me to predict a future step.
germayne: So this is how you actually maintain the structure of the sequential data, right, if you are using traditional machine learning models.
germayne: Okay?
germayne: Later on in neural networks, you will see that actually there are other methods that
germayne: allows us to induce this bias into the structure of the algorithm. But generally speaking, autoregressive is a very, very strong… I'm not saying arimar, I'm saying autoregressive is a very strong way to model sequential data.
germayne: Of course, you also have the moving average, which is just the pass error. You have the intercept, same thing that you guys know, and of course, there's a differencing, how many times you need to difference. And of course, in practice, you use KPSS tests to test if it's stationary.
germayne: Okay, so, Arima, very well established, because it's been around, I do not know for how long, I think it's been around for very, very long, okay? Very good for short-term forecasting. Interpretation, I don't think there's anything much to interpret, because usually you're not using this to interpret, you're using this for prediction.
germayne: But, one more thing about Arima is that
germayne: I don't want to go into the technical details, but Arima, if you want, the takeaway, the homework for you guys is…
germayne: Go back and think about this equation.
germayne: And I want you guys to think about, if I want to make a prediction for YT plus 1, I want to make a prediction for YT plus 2.
germayne: What do I need in my dataset? I want you guys to go back and think about it.
germayne: Okay? The reason for this is because that will help you understand the underlying components of Arima.
germayne: Okay, so that will be the homework for you guys.
germayne: Okay, so I think give you guys a key takeaway, okay? The key takeaway to summarize for today, before I give too soon, I need to quickly wrap up, otherwise we don't have time.
germayne: is that time series forecasting is typically a separate field, right? I do time series forecasting for 2 years, and I don't think I'm an expert, right? I did it, I have enough exploration to do it, I read a lot of research paper, and it's still an ongoing field. People are still creating time series forecasts, right?
germayne: The M competition is something I used to follow. Unfortunately, I don't really do a lot of time series nowadays, so I don't really follow. But back then, I remember in M4,
germayne: the winner was a data scientist from Uber, and they actually shown that a hybrid method using machine learning and, again, the traditional method actually performed very well. And a lot of top winners are actually still traditional statistical models. So what's the takeaway?
germayne: takeaway is that machine learning is still not that great for time series, right? Generally, a mix is the best, okay?
germayne: Number 3.
germayne: Time series can be still done using traditional machine learning, but you need to think about how to engineer the features. What this means is, you need to understand what's the drawback of each of the current machine learning models that has been taught, and you need to think about whether it works for time series. Example that I told you.
germayne: decision trees or tree-based models cannot extrapolate, right? So therefore, how do you actually engineer that? You can still model time series models, it's not that you can't, I've done it before, right? So, you need to also think about how to model autoregressive features, because you need to think of a way to maintain the structure of the sequential data, okay?
germayne: The takeaway here also is that there's still a lot of things to explore. There's also ETS, exponential smoothing, which is what people call hot winters, triple exponential smoothing.
germayne: The textbook also covers this. I believe the notebook also has, but I'm not sure whether we have time to cover that. But this is also an alternative method to do prediction. Now, the answer will be, which one works? I don't know, right? It depends on your data set, and you need to test it out empirically.
germayne: There's also another one that I have used in the past, it's called Profit. It was actually created by Facebook. Under the hood is a general additive model, and they also use Bayesian to actually,
germayne: They use Bayesian statistics to actually determine the parameters, right? Profit had a specific use case that I needed in the past, right? But again, it's just a different method. Now, the answer here is that you guys will only learn the basic, and it's fine.
germayne: you will not learn everything, right? I was not taught ETS in school as well. I only learned Arima, but the rest is self-learned. The takeaway here is that,
germayne: there are some resources that you need, but in future, there will always be new methods, especially for time series. Time series, I don't think is solved. It's still a constantly developed, it's still constantly being developed, right? So…
germayne: I think learn to understand that algo, learn to question the method, and I think you'll be good to go.
germayne: Okay, so I think that's the takeaway for today.
germayne: Okay? All good.
germayne: Right? So I hope that this gives you some fundamental. Arima, even though you don't use it, I'm pretty sure there's a lot of very strong takeaways from it.
germayne: Okay? Okay, I will hand to Soon. I think soon you just do your best. If we cannot finish, then I think we spill over a bit on Saturday, right? I know we are not supposed to do lectures on Saturday, but I think let's do a small spillover if Sun cannot finish.
germayne: Okay, but anybody got any questions for me so far for Arima? Straightforward?
germayne: intuitively, Anybody got any questions for me?
germayne: Noel, no question is a good thing or a bad thing.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: no question usually means fuel processing.
germayne: Okay, okay.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Yeah.
germayne: Okay, take your time, right?
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Because I think today a lot of,
Low Keng Teck, Noel: A lot of big terms, we have a lot of big names.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: But I think,
Low Keng Teck, Noel: I also wonder why we do prediction now, because, no, it doesn't really work. I mean, for time.
germayne: No, it works, it works, it works, it works. What do you mean by it doesn't work? It works, it works.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Does it work? Of course. I've only seen one that really works, right? Does it work? I haven't…
germayne: It works, it works. I've done it, I've done it. I've done models for time series.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: It actually works,
germayne: us.
germayne: But again, again, right?
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Alright.
germayne: Again, right, before I give over to soon, right, it's the same thing as, let's say, the model that you do
germayne: Works or not is a very subjective thing. End of the day, you need to have business value.
germayne: Right? Correct, right.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Yeah, yeah.
germayne: is a very subjective thing, right? You can have a model, but how does it work? You need to have the business value.
germayne: Right? Yeah. Okay, anyways, soon, back to you, yeah.
Soon | NTU: Okay, thank you, Jumin.
Soon | NTU: Me…
Soon | NTU: Okay, so let's, continue with our Jupyter Notebook to go to this outline.
Soon | NTU: Y'all can see my screen, right? Go to the Arima section, right?
Soon | NTU: Okay, so we have seen, how this, Arima model, okay, works only when your, time series data is stationary.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so… And one of the ways we can, make use of.
Soon | NTU: To make your time series data stationary is via this thing called the differencing.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so… Just now, we have already gone through Okay, differencing is basically…
Soon | NTU: using the, current, your data point, okay, minus your previous, the data point of the previous, period, okay? So…
Soon | NTU: And you're going to do it for all the data points in your time series data. So basically, you are shifting all the…
Soon | NTU: This one, by one black.
Soon | NTU: And then do, computation, okay, YT minus…
Soon | NTU: YT-1, okay? And sometimes, what first differencing, when you do it only once, may not be sufficient, okay? So there may be a need to do a second differencing, or…
Soon | NTU: third differencing, okay? You all depend on, you know, the kind of time series data you have, right?
Soon | NTU: Especially those, very complex, time series data, so you may have to do it second time, the differencing, in order to remove the… this, trend. I mean, the purpose is to remove the trend, detrend, using the differencing. Now, a rim model, right.
Soon | NTU: We have already gone through, some of the, parameters, right? The P, D, and Q.
Soon | NTU: Right? Which, xunmain has already shared, okay, of course, if you… There's also another, more,
Soon | NTU: another version, sophisticated version, is to include this seasonality. So, we add one more F in front for seasonality. So, instead of PQ, we have additional PDQ in capital letters.
Soon | NTU: And then, a small M4.
Soon | NTU: the number of periods in the season. Okay, so using this notation to represent the
Soon | NTU: Sarima, I think it's not so, intuitive. Okay, so, why not we look at this notation?
Soon | NTU: Okay, maybe there's a better… Right? So usually we have PDQ,
Soon | NTU: for our non-seasonal, portion, right, AR,
Soon | NTU: this is AR, this is,
Soon | NTU: for the, the defensing, and this is for the MA.
Soon | NTU: This is for the… likewise, for the AR of the seasonal portion.
Soon | NTU: I think we can coin no.
Soon | NTU: summary map, okay? So this is a defensing for the seasonal.
Soon | NTU: variation, and we also have a MA part for the seasonal, okay? So this M, usually is Tof.
Soon | NTU: Okay, but for this kind of Arima model, okay, so these are the parameters which we need to optimize.
Soon | NTU: That means we need to find the optimal, value for each of these, P, D, and Q in order to get a very good, so-called forecasting, so-called model
Soon | NTU: Okay? Using the ARIMA modeling techniques. Okay? So, now… So let's go through…
Soon | NTU: our, the codes, right? sk time arima module has this arima, auto-arima,
Soon | NTU: classes for you to do this. Now, Arima, you can
Soon | NTU: Of course, do this, using the manual approach, okay, to just say trial and error.
Soon | NTU: to find out what are actually the optimal value for the respective PDQ, PDQ, and also the M, and so on, okay? So, this is the manual method of, you know, trial and error, okay?
Soon | NTU: You have to really depend on
Soon | NTU: Maybe a lot of the, the visual and the so-called analysis based on whatever plot and chart that you have obtained, okay, that you have seen, before.
Soon | NTU: King.
Soon | NTU: Okay?
Soon | NTU: And then… oh.
Soon | NTU: Of course, we can also do it Auto.
Soon | NTU: Right, so auto arima. Okay, so we'll also do the same thing. Okay, so instead of manually trying to find out what are actually the optimal value for this. So, for the manual method, we use… we set it to, all the…
Soon | NTU: All the parameter to 1.
Soon | NTU: and then a default for our seasonal period, 12 months. Okay, so this is a very good starting point for the manual process, but for Auto Arima, we will let the system
Soon | NTU: the Auto Arima 2D.
Soon | NTU: to find out what should be the optimal value, okay? It may not be 1, it can be 2, or it can be 0.
Soon | NTU: Okay, now, just something to… to… to share with you is, this stepwise through, right? Okay? There are actually, different, variations, okay, which you can use the auto aroma. Okay, so stepwise through is to take… leave it
Soon | NTU: to the auto-arima to do… to find the optimal mix of peak DQ for you.
Soon | NTU: Okay, now if you step into step 1 falls.
Soon | NTU: You are basically using a grid search.
Soon | NTU: Okay, you're going through all the, you know, the different permutation of your PDQ and capital PDQ, okay? So…
Soon | NTU: Now, the range of the value, right, have already been predefined
Soon | NTU: Okay, if you were to use the grid search method, but in our case, we just use a stepwise equal to true, we let the system determine the PDQ for us.
Soon | NTU: Okay, and it is more, time efficient, okay? So, because if you set it to force, it may take a longer time. I have not tried to run it using the stepwise force, but you can try it out, okay? Now, if you go to look at the, documentation of this,
Soon | NTU: The auto-arema, right?
Soon | NTU: You'll know that, okay, for Auto Arima.
Soon | NTU: Okay, you can just, search.
Soon | NTU: Auto Arimas, SK, time, and then you will get this, okay? So basically, you can see stop P,
Soon | NTU: MaxP, okay, so there are already a parameter value preset for you, but of course, you can always override it. Oh, I may want to try up to a max P of 5.
Soon | NTU: is actually at your discretion to change it to meet your particular use case, your needs, okay? This is only applicable when you set the stepwise to force using the research.
Soon | NTU: Right.
Soon | NTU: to go and, let the system to permit it, to get the optimum mix of PQD and PQD here.
Soon | NTU: Okay, but today we are going to use this, that Y is equal to true, and then we will use this model based on this
Soon | NTU: Okay, we have included this seasonal PQD as well, because we have specified a PQD of,
Soon | NTU: sorry, we have, told the auto arrayment we want to include the character PQD in our
Soon | NTU: a Riemer equation, right?
Soon | NTU: And then after training, These are the optimal parameter that you can find for us.
Soon | NTU: Okay? Now, just to take note that this one
Soon | NTU: is based on the AIC, all these… the auto arena will tell you, oh, so far this is the best model I have found.
Soon | NTU: Slightly different from the… different, PQD that you have set in your manual model.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so, very close.
Soon | NTU: But except the MA portion are not there, and also the seasonal AR is not there.
Soon | NTU: Okay? So now, if you're going to call a summary method on the auto-arima, you'll have, some information like this, okay? So, just like I've shared with you, some of the tests, okay, so this one is to test
Soon | NTU: auto-correlation, there's any, you know? And also, you have these, variance, changes, yes or no, okay? So, you can basically go to this summary result to interpret. Just try it out yourself, see whether all this value makes sense to you, okay? So this means
Soon | NTU: Your null hypothesis not rejected.
Soon | NTU: not rejected.
Soon | NTU: not rejected. So if not rejected, what does it mean? Okay, I will share the document with you after the session, okay? So now.
Soon | NTU: Now, we are comfortable with the results, okay, assuming all these statistics tests give you a very acceptable result, and then you will use this
Soon | NTU: Both the manual and the auto-arima model to predict.
Soon | NTU: With the same forecasting horizon. And these are the…
Soon | NTU: as the symmetric, mean absolute percentage error, okay? Very close.
Soon | NTU: Okay? But… From the look at it, this one seemed to be not as performing, not as good as
Soon | NTU: Comparing to the manual model, okay? So it's because of, some reasons.
Soon | NTU: Okay.
Soon | NTU: So, this manual model may be slightly overfit, because you have, taken into account an MA component, whereas this auto-arema
Soon | NTU: May be giving you a model like this, E.
Soon | NTU: Actually, 0.001, it is not statistically so.
Soon | NTU: Significant, right?
Soon | NTU: Okay? Versus, the manual with model.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so if you were to plot these two models on the same chart, okay, so they all basically more or less, look the same in terms of the forecasting value. Okay, of course.
Soon | NTU: Both seem to be a little bit, overestimated, over-forecast.
Soon | NTU: And also underestimated the actual value in the later part of the year.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so…
Soon | NTU: It is still not foolproof, but then it is a very good example to show how this arima modeling process can be automated using the auto-arima function.
Soon | NTU: Okay? No.
Soon | NTU: So,
Soon | NTU: Jermaine, do you want me to go through this
Soon | NTU: Or should we continue on Saturday?
germayne: No, I think the… I think the ACF and PACF can be a self-study exercise. I don't think it's… I don't think it's important. Is there any more? The ETS one, I think, is also out of… out of topic lah. I think that one can self-study from the book, yeah?
Soon | NTU: Okay, so I just have to, summarize, okay, so this arima parameters, okay, if you're going to do it manually, right, of course, if you do auto-arima, everything will be
Soon | NTU: done for you, okay? But if you're going to do it manually, you need to rely on… make use of this ACF and the PACF plot as the main tool to guide you, right?
Soon | NTU: Of course, along the way, you also have to make full use of the, this, statistical tests for you to make sure that, oh, there's… your series is, already stationary, because if your time series is still not stationary, then a rimmer model will not work.
Soon | NTU: Okay? So, if it's not stationary, you have to apply this state differencing on your data.
Soon | NTU: Okay, by using this, method called… okay, this is the original version. Okay, as you can see, the p-value is…
Soon | NTU: telling you, oh, this is not stationary, okay? Because it failed to reject HO.
Soon | NTU: And then, you apply the… Okay, so this is the, time series data.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Excellent.
Soon | NTU: without differencing.
Soon | NTU: And then this is weave differencing, okay? After deferencing, first differencing.
Soon | NTU: You're still not able to reject the null hypothesis, Your data is still…
Soon | NTU: non-stationary. If we do it one more time.
Soon | NTU: Again, second defensing, you will find that your… now your p-value is 0.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so this is how we actually make use of your hypothesis test, as well as your ACF plot and the PACF plot tool.
Soon | NTU: visually, you know, somewhat inspection to gauge whether you have done enough in the differencing. The intention is to remove
Soon | NTU: Your… on your decent seasonality trend, okay?
Soon | NTU: So, this is the… The, the main, the gist of it, okay?
Soon | NTU: Right?
Soon | NTU: Okay, so I'll leave it to you, to check out the, this section. Okay, so any questions you have, you probably can, ask us on Saturday, or post it in the Discord.
Chieh Cheng Lai: Just one question. So, so the second differentiating, so this is the, expected result.
Chieh Cheng Lai: So, I will expect that if the thing, the data is stationary, I will see the result, everything.
Chieh Cheng Lai: In the second graph.
Soon | NTU: After second differencing, right, okay, we are differencing based on the… Seasonal.
Soon | NTU: The first differencing is on the trend, not seasonal portion. Second differencing is on the big, D.
Soon | NTU: Okay, small d, big D, so in the end, you remove the…
Soon | NTU: And all the… all the… the noise inside.
Chieh Cheng Lai: Oh, it's not seasoned.
Soon | NTU: Now you have, yeah, you are able to reject your null hypothesis, now your alternative hypothesis telling you that, oh, this is now stationary.
Chieh Cheng Lai: Oh, okay, I understand. So, so EP goes to zero, so it's also in, remove the residue, the white noise.
Chieh Cheng Lai: as well.
Soon | NTU: This is only a test of stationery. Nothing to do with the white noise.
Chieh Cheng Lai: Okay, understood.
Soon | NTU: Okay? We have to do it step by step, lah.
Soon | NTU: Stationary is stationary. Okay, then you will proceed with the next step to see what you can do. It's… have you completed… completely removed the seasonal portion? You know, do you need to… because if I look at the chart, right, there are still some, thing sticking out, even after you have
Soon | NTU: Remove the seasonal, I mean, the different… the different thing second time. There's still something sticking out.
Soon | NTU: Okay, so that means you need to do… take further action to explain why you have some residue like this.
Chieh Cheng Lai: even the P is equal to 0.
Chieh Cheng Lai: the p-value.
Soon | NTU: P0 is not significant, but you still, based on the ACF plot, right, you still have some kind of a thing, because any dot within this blue band is not significant.
Soon | NTU: Okay, but you have something…
Soon | NTU: Sticking out like this, you have to find, hey, is there a reason why it's sticking out like this?
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Maybe, maybe, maybe it's outlier. I mean, see the first one. The first one is so.
Soon | NTU: Yeah, yeah, so yeah.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: The outlier, right.
Soon | NTU: really something only happened at this point, and not in the others. Okay, so you have to really go and, take…
Soon | NTU: Further action to investigate lah.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: But, but after, after all your, all your…
Low Keng Teck, Noel: all your mathematical acrobatics, we can still know what this point… what is this point,
Low Keng Teck, Noel: I mean, like, is there a direct correlation with this point to the original point? I thought that might not… it might be.
Soon | NTU: Based on the… this, right? So, you see, interpreting the result, right, based on the ACF and PSCF, so there is still some spike at, some certain length, so suggesting possible MA1.
Soon | NTU: And also the seasoned MA.
Soon | NTU: Okay, suggesting only lah, but whether it is really so, you have to go and No, I think…
Low Keng Teck, Noel: I think finding out will be very tedious, man. Not sure if it will be.
Soon | NTU: Yeah, yeah. That's why Auto Arima comes in, you know.
Soon | NTU: Okay.
Soon | NTU: Thank you so much, for the attention, and… Over to you, Jamin.
germayne: Okay, okay, yeah, thanks soon. Yeah, yeah, so you can see why I don't want to teach the ACF and P. I don't think it's practical lah. Just use the AutoRML. In practice, people do use AutoRML. You don't spend too much time.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Oh, God, yeah.
germayne: I remember.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Hiring year.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: No, it's not. Yeah, that's what I don't understand, though. In the beginning of the lesson, you talked about the T… TRS, TSR.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Then, like, towards the end, like, this TSR is, like, a Hindu and something that I gotta take out.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Why do we have to do that?
germayne: No, no, no, it's only for this model. Other models, you don't have to take out the trend.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Oh, okay, okay.
germayne: Yeah, it's only Arima.
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Okay, okay. Thank you for clarifying, because I was like…
Low Keng Teck, Noel: Why so funny thing? Okay, okay, okay.
germayne: Arima's principle is you are not modeling the trend and seasonal.
germayne: To some extent, lah. You want to make sure that the data is stationary, so then you can model that portion.
germayne: You're not trying to predict with the trend.
germayne: But if you find other methods, like exponential smoothing, there's a different way to model the trend.
germayne: Just different methodologies, just different… different concept.
germayne: Yeah, there's no… there is no… I think you have to test out empirically what works better.
germayne: Yo.
germayne: It's just like when you do the Kaggle, do you guys know what worked better? I'm quite sure you guys try different stuff, right?
germayne: I think, I think, I think in the end of the competition, we will have the top two teams to share what they do.
germayne: Okay, but I can see that the placement changed almost every day, so you guys can continue trying.
germayne: Yeah.
germayne: Okay.
germayne: Wait let me log into the Slido. Okay, but congrats! You guys finished 3.6!
germayne: How are you guys feeling?
germayne: What?
germayne: Next week, we will have… next week will be more exciting.
germayne: In a good way.
germayne: Yeah.
germayne: Okay, so I think, I think, I think, I think the analogy for you guys today, right, I think you guys can start to do the… you guys can start to do the… so what do you guys learned today?
germayne: I would say, right, if to you, time series is something that is not relevant, then I think it's okay, right? Nobody needs to know every single thing. If time series is something that's super valuable for your work, then of course, you can have the motivation to invest time to go into it.
germayne: Okay? But if you feel like time series is just not something that you foresee yourself doing, then I think it's okay.
germayne: Alright.
germayne: Okay, so what's the… what's the key takeaway for today? Yeah, for time series, yes.
germayne: Oh, good to see that you guys still have that energy.
germayne: Yeah, but I think, I think it's good. We are doing, we are doing well. We are… we are really close to finishing. I think the next four topics
germayne: you guys will definitely feel that maybe there's even stronger motivation, because it will kind of give you the background to understand how the existing hype on AI works, right? We are going to… we are going to build the building blocks, the foundation. Again.
germayne: The amount of lessons done is just…
germayne: not doing justice to the full, true curriculum. We have 4 topics to talk about neural networks, but obviously neural network can be a module on its own, right? So… but I believe it will still be very interesting, because now at least you guys will understand
germayne: more about, you know, when people talk about deep learning, people talk about neural networks, people talk about large language model, what does it actually mean under the hood? And we will need to use all the foundation that we have so far. Alright, everything will all be relevant, yeah?
germayne: Okay, so I think good. Today is really just about time series. We really go through very basic, foundation for time series.
germayne: But my advice is the textbook is, no, normally, I don't really recommend, like, textbooks. So, like, for example, there are very traditional machine learning textbooks, but a lot of it are very academia, so I'm not, I'm not, like, really recommending them to you.
germayne: But for example, if you're someone that… oh, you know, when I say that the maximum likelihood estimation is, like, mean square error.
germayne: Right? You guys are interested in that. Then, for example, those textbooks would be interesting, right? But I think for FPP, it's actually more applied, it's more on applied time series, so I definitely think it's a very good book.
germayne: Okay.
germayne: Yeah, I think soon, thanks, appreciate for the notebook, yeah, thanks, thanks, thank you, God, you did a good job, yeah.
Soon | NTU: And you're welcome, mate to me.
germayne: Yeah.
germayne: Okay, shall I go on? I think I still see someone typing.
germayne: Can I go up.
germayne: Okay, so which portion do you guys think is the most challenging today?
germayne: Which one do you think is the hardest?
germayne: You guys will still have… you guys still have a homework? So, the final homework is to go and think about how is AutoRMR applied for prediction? Like, if you want to predict, what should the inputs be?
germayne: So I think that should be the takeaway. Okay? If you can completely understand that, then I think that would then definitely mean that you have completely understand Arima.
germayne: Yeah.
germayne: Okay, so that's an extra homework for those who are interested.
germayne: Math no detail.
germayne: I think, I think, va…
germayne: Next week, actually, we'll have a lot of math.
germayne: A lot of, linear algebra, actually, next week.
germayne: Because when you think about deep learning, it's a lot of matrices.
germayne: But you need to understand matrix. So, if you guys remember all your matrix algebra.
germayne: How do you actually do a dot product between matrix?
germayne: yeah, those becomes relevant. I think some people knows what I'm talking about. If you have learned neural networks of deep learning, then…
germayne: Linear algebra is actually a foundation.
germayne: Yeah. Then, when we talk about gradient descent, it's actually talking about your derivative, basically how you do your derivative, right?
germayne: So, we'll talk a bit about that lah, and I think if you appreciate the map, then I think it will make a lot more sense, yeah.
germayne: Okay, let's go.
germayne: Okay, so how do you guys find today for the introduction of time series?
germayne: I would suggest, if you guys want to learn more, go and read the textbook, okay? I think Seasonal Arima should be Chapter 8.9.
germayne: Right? I didn't talk about seasonal Arima because it's just an extension for Arima, right? Nothing changes, right? But if you guys want to read more, I think Chapter 8.9 has it. So for those of you who are very interested in time series, the book will be perfect.
germayne: Okay, even though the code is in our code, but I don't think the code really matters. I think the concept will still be very relevant.
germayne: Yeah.
germayne: Okay, so those of you who, let's say, think about time series and interested, you guys can ask me on the side, right? I can give you guys advice on what to model.
germayne: For time series. That's why I think the most memorable was that I have used to talk a student, and I think she had a capstone for her company, that she needs to do prediction for the shoes inventory.
germayne: And I think they managed to do… they managed to implement it.
germayne: Okay, let's continue. I think today's SAMS is great. Okay, that's good, that's good.
germayne: Okay, so what do you think was a good takeaway for today?
germayne: For today's class.
germayne: What's a good takeaway from today?
germayne: Anything that was mind-blowing?
germayne: Yes, the notebook has a lot of content, yeah.
germayne: Correct.
germayne: Exactly. Oh, okay, okay. That's a very good takeaway, that's actually a very good takeaway. That is a very fantastic takeaway. Actually, it looks like, yes, exactly. Exactly. It's a linear model.
germayne: So that's the beauty, right? When you start to learn a lot of things, you start to find concepts that are very similar, like, that is not, like, something new. You start to realize that, oh, actually, there's something that I get an intuition, and I think that's actually a very good sign of, you know, you are able to melt different things together. I think that's a good thing.
germayne: Yep.
germayne: Okay, so what… last… for the last one, what do you think are the… the areas that you think you can improve on?
germayne: Or today.
germayne: Hmm.
germayne: Ugh.
germayne: Oh, okay, so somebody says that somebody is actually… somebody needs time series. Okay, I do not know who is this, but if you… if you got any questions, right, that you want to ask for tips, right, for your… for your work.
germayne: really feel free to ask me. I mean, I cannot help you do your work, but I can provide some guidance on the direction, right? And maybe what materials to read, yeah. But yes, I think the textbook will be very relevant if, let's say, time series is important for your work, yeah.
germayne: And the last takeaway is if you have dataset, if you have access to dataset, real dataset, fantastic, then you can really try out.
germayne: Right, so it's not just an academia exercise.
germayne: Okay?
germayne: Okay, cool. I think… thanks everyone for today. I think that's… I think that's all for… that's all for today. Congrats again. We are almost done, to be honest. I think it's just 2 weeks more before we say goodbye.
germayne: Okay? Actually, it's very fast, it's just 2 more weeks.
germayne: So it's just formal lessons, and… yeah.
germayne: Okay, so I will see you guys on Saturday. What I'll do is I'll open up a thread to get questions, and I will have a small segment where I will give you guys tips for the Kaggle, and then the rest of the time will be just to do the Kaggle.
germayne: Okay?
germayne: Okay, I'll give some tips so that, if you guys are not there.
germayne: Too bad, right? I'll be giving tips, so those of you who are on there on Saturday, you will get the tips. I mean, I won't give you the answer, but I'll generally give you, like, some direction on what are some of the things that you should try to gain improvements in the score, okay? So I will tell that to everyone, so it'll be a fair play. I'm not going to release any
germayne: secret or what, but I'm going to give very general, tips that you may or may not have tried. Okay, so I want to do that.
germayne: then I think, I'll open up a chat for questions. If there's any questions, you guys can ask. I think Dr. Elvin will be there on Saturday, right, to introduce himself in person.
germayne: And, yeah, I think that's all. Then we will just do the… we'll have a group exercise for Kaggle, and yeah, that will be for Saturday's agenda, or if there's any questions or things that you guys want us to go through.
germayne: Okay, Ken? Alright, all good. Okay, then all the best for those of you who are still trying the Kaggle. Yeah, I think… I think that's all.
germayne: Thank you so much. Thank you so much, everyone. Thank you, thank you. Yeah, have a good night. Thank you, see you on Saturday.
Soon | NTU: for 91.